<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mw72>
<H1><h><key1>arDa</key1><key2>arDa</key2><hom>2</hom></h><body>ardha, as, a1, am,  half, halved, forming a half <lb/>[cf. Osset. <i>ardag</i>]; <i>ardha ardha,</i> one part, the other <lb/>part; (<i>as, am</i>), m. n. the half; one part of two, a <lb/>part, a party; half; a short syllable. The accent is <lb/>on the last syllable. (<i>Ardha</i> may be compounded in <lb/>a peculiar way with an ordinal, e. g. <i>ardha-tr2iti1ya,</i> <lb/>containing (two and) the third (only) half, i. e. two <lb/>and a half; <i>ardha-c4aturtha,</i> three and a half, &amp;c.) <lb/><i>--Ardha-ka1la</i> or <i>ardha-ku1t2a, as,</i> m. an epithet <lb/>of S4iva. <i>--Ardha-kr2ita, as, a1, am,</i> half-done, half- <lb/>performed. <i>--Ardha-ketu, us,</i> m., N. of a Rudra. <lb/><i>--Ardha-kot2i1,</i> f. half a crore, five millions. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-kosha, as,</i> m. a moiety of one's treasure. <lb/><i>--Ardha-kros4a, as,</i> m. half a league. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>kha1ra, am, i1,</i> n. f. a measure, half a kha1ri1. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>gan4ga1,</i> f., N. of the river Ka1veri1. <i>--Ardha-garbha, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> Ved. in the middle of the womb. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-guc4c4ha, as,</i> m. a necklace of twenty-four <lb/>strings. <i>--Ardha-gola, as,</i> m. a hemisphere. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-c4akravartin</i> or <i>ardha-c4akrin, i1,</i> m. half a <lb/>c4akravartin; N. of the nine black Va1sudevas and the <lb/>nine enemies of Vishn2u. <i>--Ardha-c4andra, as,</i> m. <lb/>half-moon; the semicircular marks on a peacock's <lb/>tail; the semicircular scratch of the finger nail; an <lb/>arrow, the head of which is like a half-moon; the <lb/>hand bent into a semicircle or the shape of a claw, as <lb/>for the purpose of seizing or clutching abything; (<i>a1</i>), <lb/>f., N. of the plant Convolvulus Torpethum; (<i>as, a1, <lb/>am</i>), crescent-shaped, of a semilunar form. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>c4andra1ka1ra (ºra-a1kº), as, a1, am,</i> or <i>ardha- <lb/>c4andra1kr2iti, is, is, i,</i> half-moon-shaped, crescent- <lb/>shaped; (<i>as</i>), m. or (<i>is</i>), f. a meniscus. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>c4andrika1,</i> f., N. of a climbing plant. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>c4olaka, as,</i> m. a short bodice. <i>--Ardha-ja1hnavi1,</i> f., <lb/>N. of the river Ka1veri1. <i>--Ardha-tanu, us,</i> f. half a <lb/>body. <i>--Ardha-tikta, as,</i> m., N. of a plant. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-tu1ra, as,</i> m. a particular kind of musical instru- <lb/>ment. <i>--Ardha-dagdha, as, a1, am,</i> half-burnt. <lb/><i>--Ardha-divasa, as,</i> m. half a day, midday; a <lb/>day containing one half of a whole day, a day of <lb/>twelve hours. <i>--Ardha-deva, as,</i> m., Ved. demi-god. <lb/><i>--Ardha-dha1ra, am,</i> n. a knife or lancet with a <lb/>single edge, the blade two inches long, the handle six. <lb/><i>--Ardha-na1ra1yan2a, as,</i> m. a form of Vishn2u. <lb/><i>--Ardha-na1ri1s4a (ºri1-i1s4a), as,</i> m. one of the forms <lb/>of S4iva (half male and half female). <i>--Ardha-na1va, <lb/>am,</i> n. half a boat. <i>--Ardha-nis4a1,</i> f. midnight. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-pan3c4a1s4at,</i> f. twenty-five. <i>--Ardha-pan2a, am,</i> <lb/>n. a measure containing half a pan2a. <i>--Ardha-patha, <lb/>am,</i> n. half-way; (<i>e</i>), ind. midway. <i>--Ardha-pa1dika, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> having only half a foot. <i>--Ardha-pa1ra1- <lb/>vata, as,</i> m. a kind of pigeon. <i>--Ardha-pula1yita, am,</i> <lb/>n. a half-gallop, canter. <i>--Ardha-pu1rn2a, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>half-full. <i>--Ardha-prahara, as,</i> m. half a watch, one <lb/>hour and a half. <i>--Ardha-br2ihati1,</i> f., Ved. half the <lb/>usual breadth. <i>--Ardha-bha1ga, as,</i> m. a half; a <lb/>part. <i>--Ardha-bha1gika, as, i1, am,</i> or <i>ardha-bha1- <lb/>gin, i1, ini1, i,</i> taking or sharing half. <i>--Ardha-bha1j, <lb/>k, k, k,</i> taking or sharing half; (<i>k</i>), m. a sharer, <lb/>companion. <i>--Ardha-bha1skjara, as,</i> m. midday. <lb/><i>--Ardha-bhot2ika,</i> f. a kind of cake. <i>--Ardha-ma1- <lb/>gadhi1,</i> f. a variety of the Ma1gadhi1 dialect. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>ma1n2ava</i> or <i>ardha-ma1n2avaka, as,</i> m. a necklace of <lb/>twelve strings. <i>--Ardha-ma1tra1,</i> f. half a short sylla- [Page0084-c+ 79] <lb/>ble. <i>--Ardha-ma1rge,</i> ind. half-way, midway. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-ma1sa, as,</i> m. half a month; <i>ardhama1sa-s4as,</i> <lb/>ind. every half month, or fortnight. <i>--Ardhama1sa- <lb/>tama, as, a1, am,</i> or <i>ardhama1sika, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>done or happening every half month; lasting half <lb/>a month, or a fortnight. <i>--Ardha-musht2i, is,</i> m. f. <lb/>a half-clenched hand. <i>--Ardha-ya1ma, as,</i> m. half a <lb/>watch, an hour and a half. <i>--Ardha-ratha, as,</i> m. <lb/>a warrior who fights on a car along with another. <lb/><i>--Ardha-ra1tra, as,</i> m. midnight; a night contain- <lb/>ing half a whole day of twenty-four hours. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>ra1tra-samaya, as,</i> m. the time of midnight. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dhara1tra1rdhadivasa (ºra1tra-ardhaº), am,</i> n. the <lb/>equinox. <i>--Ardharc4a (ºdha-r2ic4a), as, am,</i> m. n. <lb/>half a verse or hemistich. <i>--Ardharc4a-s4as,</i> ind. in <lb/>every hemistich. <i>--Ardha-vastra-sam2vi1ta, as, a1, <lb/>am,</i> clothed or enveloped in half-garments. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>visarga, as,</i> m. the sound Visarga before <i>k, kh, p, <lb/>ph,</i> so called because its sign (<s>Z</s>) is the half of that <lb/>of Visarga (<s>H</s>). <i>--Ardha-vi1kshan2a, am,</i> n. a side- <lb/>look, a glance, a leer. <i>--Ardha-vr2iddha, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>middle-aged. <i>--Ardha-vaina1s4ika, as,</i> m., N. of the <lb/>followers of Kan2a1da (‘arguing half-perishableness’). <lb/><i>--Ardha-vya1sa, as,</i> m. the radius of a circle. <lb/><i>--Ardha-s4ata, am,</i> n. fifty; one hundred and <lb/>fifty. <i>--Ardhas4ana, am,</i> for <i>ardha1s4ana (ºdha- <lb/>as4º), am,</i> n. half a meal. <i>--Ardha-s4aphara, as,</i> <lb/>m. a kind of fish. <i>--Ardha-s4abda, as, a1, am,</i> hav- <lb/>ing a low voice. <i>--Ardha-s4esha</i> or <i>ardha1vas4esha <lb/>(ºdha-avº), as, a1, am,</i> having only half left. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha1s4ya1ma, as, a1, am,</i> half-clouded. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>s4loka, as,</i> m. half a S4loka. <i>--Ardha-san3ja1ta-s4asya, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> having its crops half-grown. <i>--Ardha- <lb/>si1rin, i1,</i> m. a cultivator, a ploughman, who takes <lb/>half the crop for his labour. <i>--Ardha-ha1ra, as,</i> <lb/>m. a necklace of sixty-four or of forty strings. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha-hrasva, am,</i> n. half a short syllable. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha1n6s4a (ºdha-an6º), as,</i> m. a half, the half. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha1n6s4in (ºdha-an6º),i1, ini1, i,</i> sharing a half. <i>--Ardha1- <lb/>ka1ra (ºdha-aº), as,</i> m. half the letter <i>a;</i> another <lb/>name for <i>avagraha,</i> q. v. <i>--Ardha1n4ga (ºdha-an4º), <lb/>am,</i> n. half the body. <i>--Ardha1rdha (ºdha-arº), <lb/>as,</i> m. half of a half, a quarter; half and half. <i>--Ar- <lb/>dha1vabhedaka (ºdha-avº), as,</i> m. pain in half the <lb/>head, hemicrania; (<i>am</i>), n. dividing in equal parts. <lb/><i>--Ardha1vas4esha (ºdha-avº), as, a1, am,</i> having <lb/>only one half left. <i>--Ardha1s4ana (ºdha-as4º), am,</i> <lb/>n. half a meal. <i>--Ardha1sana (ºdha-a1sº), am,</i> n. <lb/>half a seat (it is considered a mark of high respect to <lb/>make room for a guest on the same seat with one's <lb/>self); greeting kindly or with respect; exemption <lb/>from censure. <i>--Ardhendu (ºdha-inº), us,</i> m. a half- <lb/>moon or crescent; the semicircular impression of a <lb/>finger nail; an arrow with a crescent-shaped head; <lb/>the hand expanded in a semicircular from like a claw. <lb/><i>--Ardhendu-mauli (ºdha-inº), is,</i> m. S4iva, whose <lb/>diadem is a half-moon. <i>--Ardhendra (ºdha-inº), <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> that of which a half belongs to Indra. <lb/><i>--Ardhokta (ºdha-ukº), as, a1, am,</i> half-uttered, said <lb/>imperfectly or indistinctly. <i>--Ardhokti (ºdha-ukº), <lb/>is,</i> f. speaking indistinctly or incompletely, broken <lb/>or interrupted speech. <i>--Ardhodaya (ºdha-udº), <lb/>as,</i> m. the rising of the half-moon. <i>--Ardhodita <lb/>(ºdha-udº), as, a1, am</i> (rt. <i>i</i> with <i>ud</i>), half-risen; <lb/>(rt. <i>vad</i>), half-uttered. <i>--Ardhoruka (ºdha-u1ru), <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> reaching to the middle of the thighs; <lb/>(<i>am</i>), n. a short petticoat.</body><tail><L>5920</L><pc>0084-b</pc></tail></H1>
<H1><h><key1>ozWa</key1><key2>ozWa</key2></h><body><i>osht2ha, as,</i> m. (contracted fr. <i>ava- <lb/>stha</i>), the down-hanging lip, i. e. the upper lip (op- <lb/>posed to <i>adhara</i>), a lip in general; <i>osht2hau</i> or <lb/><i>dva1v osht2hau,</i> du. the lips, the two lips; (<i>i1</i>), f. a <lb/>creeper bearing a red flower, to which the lip is com- <lb/>monly compared (Coccinia Grandis); [cf. <i>bimba:</i> <lb/>cf. also Slav. <i>u10sta,</i> neut. pl.; <i>u10stna,</i> f.: Lat. <i>ostium.</i>] <lb/>In compounds a final <i>a</i> or <i>a1</i> before <i>osht2ha</i> may be <lb/>optionally dropped (e. g. <i>bimba + osht2ha</i> becomes <lb/>either <i>bimbosht2ha</i> or <i>bimbausht2ha,</i> ‘red-lipped,’ <lb/>and the fem. of the comp. adj. may be formed in <i>a1</i> <lb/>or <i>i1</i>). <i>--Osht2ha-karn2aka, a1s,</i> m. pl., N. of a fabu- <lb/>lous race who have their ears and lips very near <lb/>each other. <i>--Osht2ha-kopa</i> or <i>osht2ha-prakopa, as,</i> <lb/>m. a disease of the lips. <i>--Osht2ha-ja, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>produced by the lips, labial. <i>--Osht2ha-ja1ha, am,</i> n. <lb/>the root of the ear. <i>--Osht2ha-pallava, am,</i> n. a lip <lb/>or the lips. <i>--Osht2ha-put2a, am,</i> n. the cavity made <lb/>by opening the lips. <i>--Osht2ha-pushpa, am,</i> n. the <lb/>plant Pentaptera Tomentosa. <i>--Osht2ha-roga, as,</i> <lb/>m. any morbid affection of the lips. <i>--Osht2ha1dhara <lb/>(ºt2ha-adhº), au,</i> du. or <i>am,</i> n. the upper and lower <lb/>lip. <i>--Osht2hopama-phala1 (ºt2ha-upama1-phº),</i> f. the <lb/>creeper Bryonia Grandis, whose flower resembles <lb/>a lip.</body><tail><L>12989</L><pc>0189-c</pc></tail></H1>
<H1><h><key1>tri</key1><key2>tri</key2></h><body><i>tri, trayas</i> m. pl., <i>tisras</i> f. pl., <i>tri1n2i</i> <lb/>n. pl. (said to be fr. rt. <i>tr2i1;</i> in Ved. <i>tri1</i> occurs for <lb/><i>tri1n2i</i> and <i>tri1n2a1m</i> for <i>traya1n2a1m</i>), three; [cf. Gr. <lb/><g></g> Zend <i>thri, <lb/>thri-tya, thris:</i> Lat. <i>tres, tri-a, ter-tiu-s, ter:</i> <lb/>Goth. <i>threis, thriya, thri-dya:</i> Angl. Sax. <i>threo, <lb/>thry, thri:</i> Slav. <i>triye, tre-tii,</i> ‘third:’ Lith. <i>try4s,</i> <lb/>‘three;’ <i>tre4-c4za-s,</i> ‘third:’ to <i>tisras</i> belong Old <lb/>Hib. <i>teora,</i> Cambro-Brit. f. <i>tair,</i> Armor. <i>teir.</i>] <lb/><i>--Tri-kakud, t, t, t,</i> having three peaks or points <lb/>or horns &amp;c.; (<i>t</i>), m., N. of a mountain in the <lb/>Hima1laya [cf. <i>tri-ku1t2a</i> and <i>su-vela</i>]; an epithet of <lb/>Kr2ishn2a or Vishn2u; N. of a son of S4uc4i and father <lb/>of Dharma-sa1rathi; a kind of ritual observance; the <lb/>highest, chief. <i>--Tri-kakuda, as, a1, am,</i> having <lb/>three peaks or humps &amp;c. <i>--Tri-kakubh, p, p, p,</i> <lb/>Ved. having three peaks or points; an epithet of <lb/>Indra's thunderbolt or of Indra himself; (<i>p</i>), m., N. <lb/>of a mountain; a kind of ritual observance; [cf. <i>tri- <lb/>kakud.</i>] <i>--Tri-kat2a, as,</i> m., N. of a plant (Ruellia <lb/>Longifolia), <i>= go-kshuraka;</i> [cf. <i>tri-kan2t2a.</i>] <i>--Tri- <lb/>kat2u, u,</i> n. or <i>tri-kat2uka, am,</i> n. the aggregate of <lb/>three spices, viz. black and long pepper and dry <lb/>ginger; [cf. <i>kat2u-traya.</i>] <i>--Tri-kan2t2a, am,</i> n. the <lb/>three thorny plants, a collective N. of three kinds of <lb/>Solanum, viz. <i>br2ihati1, agni-damani1,</i> and <i>duh2- <lb/>spars4a1; (as, a1, am),</i> having three thorns; (<i>as</i>), <lb/>m., N. of a plant, <i>= go-kshuraka</i> or <i>pattra-gupta;</i> <lb/>a kind of fish. <i>--Tri-kan2t2aka, as,</i> m., N. of a <lb/>plant, <i>= go-kshuraka;</i> a kind of poisonous insect; <lb/>a kind of fish (Silurus); a kind of weapon. <i>--Tri- <lb/>kadruka, a1s,</i> m. pl., Ved. probably a N. of three <lb/>peculiar Soma-vessels [cf. <i>kadru</i>], or perhaps a N. <lb/>of an oblation consisting of three offerings of the <lb/>Soma (which is of a dark-brown colour); the first <lb/>three days of the Abhi-plava festival which lasts six <lb/>days, (respectively called Jyotis, Go, and A1yus.) <lb/><i>--Trikadruki1ya, as, a1, am,</i> containing the word <lb/><i>tri-kadruka. --Tri-karn2a, as, i1, am,</i> having <lb/>three ears. <i>--Tri-karman,</i> (at the beginning of a <lb/>comp.) the three chief duties of a Bra1hman, viz. <lb/>sacrifice, study of the Vedas, and liberality (e. g. <i>tri- <lb/>karma-kr2it,</i> performing these three duties); (<i>a1, a1, <lb/>a</i>), engaging in these three actions. <i>--Tri-karsha, <lb/>am,</i> n. <i>= tri-ka1rshika. --Tri-kala1,</i> f., N. of a female <lb/>deity produced by the union of three gods for <lb/>the destruction of Andhaka. <i>--Tri-ka1n2d2a, as, a1, [Page0388-c+ 81] <lb/>am,</i> consisting of three parts or divisions; forty- <lb/>eight cubits long; (<i>as</i> or <i>am</i>), m. or n. (?), a work <lb/>consisting of three parts, especially the dictionary of <lb/>Amara-sin6ha, also called Amara-kosha. <i>--Trika1n2d2a- <lb/>c4inta1-man2i, is,</i> m. or <i>trika1n2d2a-viveka, as,</i> m., N. <lb/>of commentaries on this work. <i>--Trika1n2d2a-man- <lb/>dana,</i> N. of a work. <i>--Trika1n2d2a-s4esha, as,</i> m. a <lb/>vocabulary in three chapters supplementary to the <lb/>Amara-kosha by Purushottama. <i>--Tri-ka1ya, as, a1, <lb/>am,</i> having three bodies; (<i>as</i>), m., N. of Buddha or of <lb/>a Buddha. <i>--Tri-ka1rshika, am,</i> n. the three contracting <lb/>(<i>ka1rshika</i> fr. rt. <i>kr2ish</i>) substances, dry ginger, Ati- <lb/>visha1, and Musta1; [cf. <i>tri-karsha, danta-karshan2a.</i>] <lb/><i>--Tri-ka1la, am,</i> n. the three times, viz. past, <lb/>present, and future time; morning, noon, and <lb/>evening; the present, past, and future tenses of a <lb/>verb; (<i>am</i>), ind. three times, thrice; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), <lb/>connected with or relating to the three times (past, <lb/>present, and future). <i>--Trika1la-jn3a, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>knowing the three times, omniscient; (<i>as</i>), m. a <lb/>divine sage; a deity; a N. of Buddha, the founder of <lb/>the Buddhist religion. <i>--Trika1la-dars4in, i1, ini1, i,</i> see- <lb/>ing (or knowing) the past, present, and future, omni- <lb/>scient; (<i>i1</i>), m. a R2ishi or divine sage; N. of Buddha. <lb/><i>--Trika1la-vid, t, t, t,</i> knowing the three times; (<i>t</i>), <lb/>m. a Buddha; (with Jainas) an Arhat. <i>--Tri-kun2d2i1- <lb/>s4vara (ºd2a-i1s4º?), am,</i> n., N. of a Tantra. <i>--Tri- <lb/>ku1t2a, as, a1, am,</i> having three peaks or humps or <lb/>elevations &amp;c.; (<i>as</i>), m., N. of several mountains, <lb/><i>= tri-kakud</i> and <i>su-vela;</i> a mountain in Ceylon <lb/>on the top of which Lan4ka1, the capital of Ra1van2a, <lb/>was situated; (<i>am</i>), n. sea-salt prepared by evapo- <lb/>ration. <i>--Triku1t2a-lavan2a, am,</i> n. a peculiar kind <lb/>of salt <i>(= dron2i1-lavan2a). --Triku1t2a-vat, a1n,</i> m., N. <lb/>of a mountain. <i>--Tri-ku1rc4aka, am,</i> n. a sort of <lb/>knife with three edges. <i>--Trikaika (ºka-eka),</i> Ved., <lb/>N. of an Eka1ha; [cf. <i>eka-trika.</i>] <i>--Tri-kon2a, as, a1, <lb/>am</i> (borrowed fr. the Gr. <g></g>), triangular, <lb/>forming a triangle; (<i>as, a1</i>), m. f. Trapa Bispinosa; <lb/>(<i>am</i>), n. (in astron.) N. of the fifth and ninth <lb/>mansion [cf. <i>tri-kona-bhavana</i> and <i>tri-trikon2a</i>]; <lb/>the vulva; [cf. <i>tri-bhuj.</i>] <i>--Trikon2a-kun2d2a, am,</i> <lb/>n., N. of a mystical vessel in the form of a diagram. <lb/><i>--Trikon2a-phala, am,</i> n. Trapa Bispinosa. <i>--Tri- <lb/>kon2a-bhavana, am,</i> n. (in astron.) N. of the fifth <lb/>and ninth mansion. <i>--Tri-krama, as,</i> m. (according <lb/>to the Pra1tis4a1khyas) a Krama word composed of three <lb/>words or members, the middle one of which is a single <lb/>vowel. <i>--Tri-ksha1ra, am,</i> n. the three burning or <lb/>acrid substances, viz. natron, saltpetre, and borax. <lb/><i>--Tri-kshura,</i> N. of a plant, <i>= kokila1ksha. --Tri- <lb/>kha, am,</i> n. a cucumber (‘having three cavities’). <lb/><i>--Tri-khat2va, am, i1,</i> n. f. three beds collectively. <lb/><i>--Tri-khan2d2a,</i> the earth as divided into three por- <lb/>tions. <i>--Tri-kharva, a1s,</i> m. pl., Ved., N. of a particu- <lb/>lar school of theologians. <i>--Tri-gan4ga, am,</i> n., N. <lb/>of a Ti1rtha; [cf. <i>sapta-gan4ga.</i>] <i>--Tri-gan2a, as,</i> <lb/>m. the aggregate of the three objects of existence, <lb/>viz. virtue (<i>dharma</i>), pleasure or the ‘dulce’ (<i>ka1ma</i>), <lb/>and wealth or the ‘utile’ (<i>artha</i>); [cf. <i>tri-varga.</i>] <lb/><i>--Tri-gata, as, a1, am,</i> tripled; gone or done in three <lb/>ways; (<i>am</i>), n. the expression of different senses by the <lb/>same word. <i>--Tri-gandhaka, am,</i> n. <i>= tri-ja1taka, <lb/>--Tri-gambhi1ra,</i> see under <i>gabhi1ra. --Tri-garta, <lb/>a1s,</i> m. pl., N. of a people inhabiting the modern <lb/>Lahore; (<i>as</i>), m. a prince of the Tri-gartas; the <lb/>country of the Tri-gartas; a particular method of <lb/>calculation; (<i>a1</i>), f. a lascivious woman, a wanton; <lb/>a woman in general; a kind of cricket (<i>= ghur- <lb/>guri1, ghurgurika1</i>); a pearl. <i>--Trigartaka, a1s,</i> <lb/>m. pl. <i>= tri-garta. --Trigarta-ra1ja, as,</i> and <i>tri- <lb/>garta-ra1jan, a1,</i> m. king of Tri-garta. <i>--Tri-gar- <lb/>tika, as,</i> m. the country of the Tri-gartas. <i>--Tri- <lb/>gun2a, a1s,</i> m. pl. the three qualities or constituents <lb/>of nature and every existing thing, i. e. <i>sat-tva, <lb/>rajas,</i> and <i>tamas; (as, a1, am),</i> consisting of three <lb/>threads or strings; threefold, three times repeated, <lb/>thrice, triple, treble (e. g. <i>sapta trigun2a1ni dina1ni,</i> <lb/>three times seven days); containing the three Gun2as <lb/>or properties; (<i>am</i>), ind. in three ways, three times, <lb/>thrice. <i>--Trigun2a1-karn2a, as, i1, am,</i> whose ears [Page0389-a+ 81] <lb/>have two slits dividing them into three parts (as a <lb/>mark of distinction). <i>--Trigun2a1-kr2ita, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>thrice ploughed (a field &amp;c.). <i>--Tri-gra1mi1,</i> f. an <lb/>assemblage of three villages, N. of a place. <i>--Tri- <lb/>gra1hin, i1, in2i1, i,</i> extending to the length of three <lb/>(padya1s). <i>--Tri-c4akshus, us,</i> m. ‘triocular,’ ‘three- <lb/>eyed,’ an epithet of Kr2ishn2a (more properly of S4iva). <lb/><i>--Tri-c4atuh2-karn2a,</i> the third and fourth hypo- <lb/>tenuses. <i>--Tri-c4atura, a1s, a1s, a1n2i,</i> pl. three or <lb/>four. <i>--Tri-c4aturdas4a, au,</i> &amp;c., du. the thir- <lb/>teenth and fourteenth. <i>--Tric4atva1rin6s4a, as, i1, am</i> <lb/>(fr. the next), the forty-third. <i>--Tri-c4atva1rin6s4at, <lb/>t,</i> f. forty-three. <i>--Tri-c4aritra (?), am,</i> n. three <lb/>kinds of characters, (perhaps a wrong reading for <lb/><i>stri1-c4aritra;</i> cf. <i>tri-gu1d2ha.</i>) <i>--Tri-c4it, t, t, t,</i> con- <lb/>sisting of three layers or seats of sacrificial grass. <lb/><i>--Tri-c4i1vara, am,</i> n. the three vestments of the <lb/>Buddhist ascetic. <i>--Trijagaj-janani1,</i> f. the mother of <lb/>the three worlds, an epithet of Pa1rvati1. <i>--Tri-jagat, <lb/>t,</i> n. or <i>tri-jagati1,</i> f. the triple world, i. e. heaven, <lb/>the intermediate region, and earth, or heaven, earth, <lb/>and the lowerworld. <i>--Trijagan-mohini1,</i> f. confound- <lb/>ing the minds of the (inhabitants of the) three worlds, <lb/>a form of Durga1 (?). <i>--Tri-jat2a, as, a1, am,</i> wearing <lb/>three braids of hair; (<i>as</i>), m. an epithet of S4iva; <lb/>N. of a Bra1hman; (<i>a1</i>), f., N. of a Ra1kshasi1 who <lb/>was friendly to Si1ta1; N. of a tree, <i>= vilva,</i> Ægle <lb/>Marmelos. <i>--Trijat2a1-svapna-dars4ana, am,</i> n. ‘the <lb/>dream of Tri-jat2a1,’ N. of a chapter in the fifth book <lb/>of the Ra1ma1yan2a. <i>--Tri-ja1ta</i> or <i>tri-ja1taka, am,</i> n. <lb/>three spices collectively, viz. mace, cardamoms, and <lb/>Laurus Cassia (cinnamon). <i>--Tri-ji1va1,</i> f. the sine <lb/>of three signs or ninety degrees, a radius. <i>--Tri- <lb/>jya1,</i> f. = the preceding. <i>--Tri-n2ata, as, a1, am</i> (fr. <lb/><i>tri-nata</i>), bent in three places, epithet of a bow; <lb/>(<i>a1</i>), f. a bow; [cf. <i>tr2in2ata1.</i>] <i>--Tri-n2ayana, as,</i> m. <lb/>[cf. <i>tri-nayana</i>], ‘three-eyed,’ an epithet of S4iva. <lb/><i>--Tri-n2avan</i> or <i>tri-n2ava</i> (fr. <i>tri+navan</i>), consisting <lb/>of three times nine or twenty-seven parts, connected <lb/>with the Tri-n2ava Stoma; three times nine, i. e. twenty- <lb/>seven; <i>trin2ava-sa1hasra,</i> twenty-seven thousand; [cf. <lb/><i>tri-saptan.</i>] <i>--Tri-n2a1c4iketa, as, a1, am,</i> one who <lb/>has thrice kindled the fire called Na1c4iketa; (<i>as</i>), <lb/>m. an epithet of Na1ra1yan2a (perhaps as worshipped <lb/>with this fire); (according to Kullu1ka Bhat2t2a on <lb/>Manu III. 185, <i>tri-n2a1c4iketa</i> means either ‘a part <lb/>of the Adhvaryu or Yajur-veda,’ or ‘a vow connected <lb/>with it,’ or ‘one who performs this vow.’) <i>--Tri- <lb/>n2a1man, a1, a1, a,</i> Ved. having three names, epithet <lb/>of a deity, perhaps of Agni. <i>--Tri-n2i1ta1,</i> f. a wife, <lb/>(‘thrice married,’ according to the belief that a girl <lb/>belongs to Soma, Gandharva and Agni, before she <lb/>obtains a human husband.) <i>--Tri-taksha, am, i1,</i> n. f. <lb/>(fr. <i>tri-takshan</i>), an association of three carpenters. <lb/><i>--Tri-tas,</i> ind. on three sides, from every side. <i>--Tri- <lb/>ta1,</i> f. or <i>tri-tva, am,</i> n. a triad, a trinity, an assemblage <lb/>of three. <i>--Tri-trikon2a, am,</i> n. (in astronomy) N. of <lb/>the ninth mansion; [cf. <i>tri-kon2a</i> and <i>trikon2a-bha- <lb/>vana.</i>] <i>--Tri-dan2d2a, am,</i> n. the three staves of a <lb/>mendicant Bra1hman who has resigned the world, <lb/>(these staves are tied together so as to form one); <lb/>triple subjection of words, thoughts, and acts; the <lb/>state of a religious ascetic; (<i>i1</i>), f., N. of a literary <lb/>work. <i>--Tri-dan2d2aka, am,</i> n. the three staves of a <lb/>mendicant Bra1hman described above. <i>--Tridan2d2a- <lb/>dha1ran2a, am,</i> n. carrying three staves tied together. <lb/><i>--Tri-dan2d2in, i1,</i> m. a wandering mendicant or <lb/>devotee who has resigned worldly pursuits and carries <lb/>three long bamboo staves tied together in his right <lb/>hand; the religious man who has obtained a com- <lb/>mand over his words, thoughts, and actions, or mind, <lb/>body, and speech; [cf. <i>eka-dan2d2in.</i>] <i>--Tri-dat, an, <lb/>ati1, at,</i> having three teeth. <i>--Tri-dala1,</i> f. a creeping <lb/>plant, Cissus Pedata. <i>--Tri-dalika1</i> or (according to <lb/>some) <i>tri-da1lika1,</i> f., N. of a plant, <i>= c4arma-kasha1. <lb/>--Tri-das4a, a1s,</i> m. pl. (fr. <i>tri-das4an</i>), three times <lb/>ten, i. e. thirty; the three times ten or thirty <lb/>deities, i. e. in round numbers a N. for the thirty- <lb/>three deities, not including Brahma1, Vishn2u, and <lb/>S4iva, viz. the twelve A1dityas, eight Vasus, eleven <lb/>Rudras, and two As4vins; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), divine; (<i>as</i>), [Page0389-b+ 81] <lb/>m. a god, a deity, an immortal; (<i>am</i>), n. the <lb/>residence of the thirty-three deities, i. e. heaven. <lb/><i>--Tridas4a-guru, us,</i> m. ‘the preceptor of the gods,’ <lb/>i. e. Br2ihas-pati, regent of the planet Jupiter. <i>--Tri- <lb/>das4a-gopa</i> or <i>tridas4a-gopaka, as,</i> m. a fire-fly, <i>= <lb/>indra-gopa,</i> q. v. <i>--Tridas4a-tva, am,</i> n. the state <lb/>or condition of a god, divinity, divine nature. <i>--Tri- <lb/>das4a-di1rghika1,</i> f. ‘the heavenly lake,’ epithet of <lb/>the Gan4ga1. <i>--Tridas4a-nadi1,</i> f. the heavenly river, <lb/>the Gan4ga1. <i>--Tridas4a-pati, is,</i> m. the chief of <lb/>the gods, Indra. <i>--Tridas4apati-s4astra, am,</i> n. <lb/>Indra's weapon, the thunderbolt. <i>--Tridas4a-prati- <lb/>paksha, as,</i> m. an adversary of the gods. <i>--Tridas4a- <lb/>man3jari1,</i> f. <i>= tulasi1,</i> basil. <i>--Tridas4a-vadhu1, u1s,</i> <lb/>f. or <i>tridas4a-vanita1,</i> f. a nymph of Indra's heaven, <lb/>an Apsaras, a goddess. <i>--Tridas4a-s4resht2ha, as,</i> m. <lb/>‘the best of the thirty-three deities,’ a N. of Agni; of <lb/>Brahma1. <i>--Tridas4a-sarshapa, as,</i> m. <i>= deva-sar- <lb/>shapa. --Tridas4a1n4kus4a (ºs4a-an4º), as,</i> m. the <lb/>thunderbolt (‘divine goad’). <i>--Tridas4a1c4a1rya (ºs4a- <lb/>a1c4º), as,</i> m. <i>= tridas4a-guru</i> above. <i>--Tridas4a1dhi- <lb/>pati (ºs4a-adhº), is,</i> m. ‘lord of the thirty-three <lb/>deities,’ a N. of S4iva. <i>--Tridas4a1yana (ºs4a-ayº), <lb/>as,</i> m. ‘the refuge of the deities,’ i. e. to whom the <lb/>deities resort, an epithet of Na1ra1yan2a; [cf. <i>brahma1- <lb/>yan2a</i> and <i>loka1yana.</i>] <i>--Tridas4a1yudha (ºs4a-a1yº), <lb/>am,</i> n. ‘the divine bow,’ the rainbow; a thunder- <lb/>bolt. <i>--Tridas4a1ri (ºs4a-ari), is,</i> m. ‘enemy of the <lb/>gods,’ an Asura, a demon, a Titan. <i>--Tridas4a1ri- <lb/>ra1jan, a1,</i> m. ‘king of the demons,’ a N. of Ra1van2a. <lb/><i>--Tridas4a1laya (ºs4a-a1lº), as,</i> m. the residence of <lb/>the gods, Svarga, Indra's heaven or paradise, the <lb/>mountain Su-meru; an inhabitant of the divine world, <lb/>a god. <i>--Tridas4a1va1sa (ºs4a-a1vº), as,</i> m. the resi- <lb/>dence of the gods, heaven. <i>--Tridas4a1ha1ra (ºs4a- <lb/>a1hº), as,</i> m. the food of the gods, i. e. Amr2ita or <lb/>ambrosia. <i>--Tridas4i1-bhu1ta, as, a1, am,</i> become <lb/>divine or immortal. <i>--Tridas4endra (ºs4a-inº)</i> or <lb/><i>tridas4es4a (ºs4a-i1s4º), as,</i> m. ‘the chief of the thirty- <lb/>three deities,’ epithet of Indra; of S4iva; of Brahma1, <lb/>&amp;c. <i>--Tridas4es4a-dvish, t2,</i> m. epithet of Ra1van2a <lb/>or any demon. <i>--Tridas4es4vara (ºs4a-i1s4º) = tri- <lb/>das4endra; (i1),</i> f., N. of Durga1. <i>--Tridas4es4vara- <lb/>dvish = tridas4es4a-dvish. --Tri-da1lika1,</i> f. for <i>tri- <lb/>dalika1,</i> q. v. <i>--Tri-dina, am,</i> n. three days col- <lb/>lectively. <i>--Tridina-spr2is4, k,</i> m. conjunction or con- <lb/>currence of three lunations with one solar day. <lb/><i>--Tri-diva, am,</i> n. the space within the third sky, <lb/>i. e. the innermost or most sacred part of the sky, <lb/>heaven; the sky, atmosphere; paradise; (<i>a1</i>), f., N. <lb/>of a river; cardamoms. <i>--Tridiva1dhi1s4a (ºva-adhº)</i> <lb/>or <i>tridives4a (ºva-i1s4º)</i> or <i>tridives4vara (ºva-i1s4º), <lb/>as,</i> m. ‘the lord of Tri-diva or heaven,’ an epithet of <lb/>Indra; a god, a deity. <i>--Tridivodbhava1 (ºva-udº),</i> <lb/>f. small cardamoms. <i>--Tridivaukas (ºva-okº), a1s,</i> <lb/>m. an inhabitant of Tri-diva, a celestial, a god. <i>--Tri- <lb/>dr2is4, k,</i>  m. ‘triocular,’ ‘three-eyed,’ an epithet of <lb/>S4iva. <i>--Tri-dosha, am,</i> n. disorder of the three <lb/>humors of the body, vitiation of the bile, blood, <lb/>and phlegm. <i>--Tridosha-ghna, as, i1, am,</i> correcting <lb/>the vitiated state of the three humors. <i>--Tridosha- <lb/>ja, as,</i> m. disease &amp;c. proceeding from disorder of <lb/>the three humors of the body. <i>--Tri-dhanvan, a1,</i> <lb/>m., N. of a prince or father of Trayya1run2a. <i>--Tri- <lb/>dha1,</i> ind. adv. in three ways, in three parts, in three <lb/>places, triply, trebly; <i>tridha1-kr2i,</i> to do in three <lb/>ways, to make threefold. <i>--Tri-dha1tu, us, us, u,</i> <lb/>consisting of three elements or ingredients, triple, <lb/>threefold, thrice repeated (used like <i>triplex</i> in Lat. <lb/>to denote excessive), tripartite; (Sa1y.) causing the <lb/>well-being of the three humors; (<i>us</i>), m. a N. of <lb/>Gan2es4a; (<i>u</i>), n. the aggregate of three minerals or <lb/>of the three humors; the triple world. <i>--Tridha1tu- <lb/>s4r2in4ga, as,</i> m., Ved. having a tripartite horn, having <lb/>horns or flames of three colours, red, white, and <lb/>black (with smoke), an epithet of Agni. <i>--Tridha1- <lb/>tva, am,</i> n. the state of being threefold or in three <lb/>parts, tripartition. <i>--Tri-dha1man, a,</i> n. probably <i>= <lb/>tri-diva; (a1, a1, a),</i> belonging or relating to the <lb/>three worlds or regions; having three residences, <lb/>&amp;c.; (<i>a1</i>), m. an epithet of Vishn2u; N. of Vya1sa [Page0389-c+ 81] <lb/>(= Vishn2u) in the tenth Dva1para; an epithet of <lb/>S4iva; Agni or fire; death. <i>--Tridha1-mu1rti, is,</i> f. a <lb/>girl three years of age representing the deity Durga1 <lb/>at her festivals. <i>--Tri-dha1raka, as,</i> m. ‘having three <lb/>edges,’ the plants Scirpus Kysoor and Euphorbia <lb/>Antiquorum. <i>--Tri-dha1ra-snuhi1,</i> f., N. of a plant, <lb/><i>= dha1ra1-snuhi1, try-as4ra. --Tri-nagari1,</i> f. the three <lb/>cities. <i>--Tri-nayana, as, a1, am,</i> triocular, three- <lb/>eyed; (<i>as</i>), m. an epithet of Rudra-S4iva; (<i>a1</i>), f. <lb/>epithet of Durga1; [cf. <i>tri-n2ayana.</i>] <i>--Tri-navata, <lb/>as, i1, am</i> (fr. <i>tri-navati</i>), the ninety-third. <i>--Tri- <lb/>navati, is,</i> f. ninety-three. <i>--Trinavati-tama, as, <lb/>i1, am,</i> the ninety-third. <i>--Tri-na1ka, am,</i> n., Ved. <lb/><i>= tri-diva. --Tri-na1bha, as, a1, am,</i> having three <lb/>navels or centres or central points; whose navel sup- <lb/>ports the three worlds. <i>--Tri-na1bhi, is, is, i, = <lb/>tri-na1bha. --Tri-nidhana, am,</i> n., N. of a Sa1man <lb/>(generally in connection with the names <i>a1gneyam, <lb/>a1yasyam,</i> and <i>tva1sht2ri1-sa1ma</i>). <i>--Tri-nishka, as, <lb/>a1, am, = tri-naishkika,</i> worth three Nishkas. <i>--Tri- <lb/>netra, as, i1, am,</i> triocular; (<i>as</i>), m. an epithet of <lb/>Rudra-S4iva; N. of a prince; (<i>i1</i>), f. <i>= va1ra1hi1- <lb/>kanda,</i> the root of Yam (Dioscorea). <i>--Trinetra- <lb/>c4u1d2a1-man2i, is,</i> m. ‘the crest of the three-eyed,’ <lb/>i. e. the moon (worn by S4iva as his crest). <i>--Tri- <lb/>paksha, am,</i> n. a period of three fortnights or six <lb/>weeks. <i>--Tri-pac4c4has,</i> ind. adv. (<i>tri+pad+s4as</i>), <lb/>by three Pa1das. <i>--Tripan3c4a1s4a, as, i1, am</i> (fr. <i>tri- <lb/>pan3c4a1s4at</i>), the fifty-third; containing or consisting <lb/>of fifty-three. <i>--Tri-pan3c4a1s4at, t,</i> f. fifty-three; [cf. <lb/><i>trayah2-pan3c4a1s4at</i> under <i>trayas.</i>] <i>--Tripan3c4a1s4at- <lb/>tama, as, i1, am,</i> the fifty-third. <i>--Tri-pat2u, u,</i> n. <lb/>the three saline substances, stone-salt (<i>= saindhava</i>), <lb/>Vid2-lavan2a, and black salt <i>(= ka1c4a). --Tri-pata1ka, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> (with <i>hasta</i>) the hand with three fingers <lb/>stretched out or erect; (with <i>lala1t2a</i>) the forehead <lb/>marked naturally with three horizontal lines or <lb/>wrinkles. <i>--Tri-pati1,</i> f., N. of a place of pilgrimage. <lb/><i>--Tri-pattra, as,</i> m. three-leaved, trifoliate, the <lb/>plant Ægle Marmelos <i>(= vilva); (am),</i> n. <i>= c4an2- <lb/>d2a1la-kanda,</i> a kind of bulbous plant. <i>--Tri-pat- <lb/>traka, as,</i> m. the Kin6s4uka tree, Butea Frondosa. <lb/><i>--Tri-patha, am,</i> n. the three paths or ways, viz. <lb/>the sky, atmosphere, and earth, or the sky, earth, <lb/>and lower world; a place where three roads meet; <lb/>(<i>a1</i>), f. epithet of Mathura1. <i>--Tripatha-ga1</i> or <i>tri- <lb/>patha-ga1mini1,</i> f. ‘flowing through heaven, earth, <lb/>and the lower regions,’ an epithet of the Gan4ga1. <lb/><i>--Tri-pad</i> or <i>tri-pa1d, -pa1t, -pa1t</i> or <i>-padi1, -pat,</i> <lb/>Ved. ‘three-footed,’ ‘tripod,’ epithet of Vishn2u (as <lb/>pacing the universe in three steps; cf. <i>tri-vikrama</i>); <lb/>epithet of Fever personified as a demon or evil <lb/>spirit and represented with three feet and three <lb/>hands, (probably symbolizing the cold, hot, and <lb/>sweating stages of fever); having three steps; con- <lb/>taining three Pa1das; trinomial; (<i>t</i>), m., N. of a <lb/>Daitya; (<i>-padi1</i>), f. the girth of an elephant; the <lb/>plant Cissus Pedata (<i>= godha1-padhi1</i>); a kind of <lb/>metre in Pra1kr2it; (according to Pa1n2. IV. 1, 9, the <lb/>f. must be <i>tri-pada1</i> when agreeing with <i>r2ic4,</i> e. g. <lb/><i>tri1pada1 r2ik,</i> a verse containing three Pa1das, cf. the <lb/>next.) <i>--Tri-pada, as, a1, am,</i> three-footed; having <lb/>three divisions (as a stanza); containing a measure <lb/>of three feet; containing three words; (<i>a1</i>), f., N. of <lb/>a plant, <i>= han6sa-padi1; (am),</i> n. a tripod; three <lb/>words. <i>--Tri-padika1,</i> f. a stand with three feet. <lb/><i>--Tri-panna, as,</i> m., N. of one of the ten horses <lb/>of the moon. <i>--Tri-parikra1nta, as, a1, am,</i> one <lb/>who walks thrice round the sacred fire or who cir- <lb/>cumambulates the three sacred fires. <i>--Tri-parn2a, <lb/>as, i1, am,</i> three-leaved, trefoil; (<i>as</i>), m. Butea <lb/>Frondosa; (<i>a1</i>), f. wild hemp; (<i>i1</i>), f., N. of several <lb/>plants, Desmodium Gangeticum, <i>= s4a1la-parn2i1,</i> wild <lb/>cotton, wild hemp, <i>= pr2is4ni-parn2i1-bheda</i> and <i>vana- <lb/>ka1rpa1si1,</i> Sanseviera Ceylanica; a kind of bulbous <lb/>plant, <i>= tri-parn2ika1. --Tri-parn2ika1,</i> f., N. of <lb/>several plants, a kind of bulbous plant (<i>= br2ihat- <lb/>pattra1,</i> &amp;c.); Carpopogon Pruriens; Alhagi Mau- <lb/>rorum. <i>--Tri-parya1ya, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. having <lb/>three folds or plaits. <i>--Tri-pas4u, us, us, u,</i> having <lb/>three victims. <i>--Tri-pastya, as,</i> m., Ved. ‘having [Page0390-a+ 81] <lb/>three dwellings,’ an epithet of Agni. <i>--Tri-pa1jasya, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> Ved. having three flanks or sides; (Sa1y.) <lb/>having three breasts (or seasons). <i>--Tri-pa1t2a, as,</i> <lb/>m. intersection of a prolonged side and perpendicular <lb/>(in a quadrangular figure); the figure formed by such <lb/>intersection. <i>--Tripa1t2hin, i1, ini1, i</i> (fr. <i>tri-pa1t2ha</i>), <lb/>familiar with the three Pa1t2has, (probably with the <lb/><i>sam2hita1, pada,</i> and <i>krama-pa1t2ha,</i> q. v.) <i>--Tri- <lb/>pa1n2a, as, i1, am</i> (probably a Pra1kr2it form for <i>tri- <lb/>parn2a</i> or <i>traiparn2a</i>), made of the plant Tri-parn2i1. <lb/><i>--Tri-pa1d,</i> see <i>tri-pad. --Tri-pa1da, as,</i> m. a <lb/>constellation or asterism of which three-fourths are <lb/>included under one sign of the zodiac; a stand with <lb/>three feet?; (<i>i1</i>), f. a kind of Mimosa. <i>--Tri-pa1daka, <lb/>as, ika1, am,</i> three-footed; (<i>ika1</i>), f., N. of a plant, <lb/><i>= han6sa-padi1,</i> a kind of Mimosa. <i>--Tri-pit2aka, <lb/>am,</i> n. the three baskets or collections of writings, <lb/>a collective N. for the three classes of Buddhist <lb/>writings, viz. Su1tra-pit2aka, Vinaya-pit2aka, and Abhi- <lb/>dharma-pit2aka. <i>--Tri-pin2d2i1,</i> f. the three sacrificial <lb/>cakes (mentioned in Manu III. 215). <i>--Tri-piba, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> drinking with three members of the body <lb/>(as with the two pendent ears and tongue); (<i>as</i>), m. <lb/>along-eared goat. <i>--Tri-pisht2apa, am,</i> n. <i>= tri-diva,</i> <lb/>the residence of the thirty-three gods, Indra's heaven; <lb/>paradise; the sky, ether; [cf. <i>tri-visht2apa.</i>] <i>--Tri- <lb/>pisht2apa-sad, t,</i> m. an inhabitant of heaven, a <lb/>deity. <i>--Tri-put2a, as, i1, am,</i> triangular; (<i>as</i>), m. <lb/>pulse, pease of three kinds; a kind of vetch, Cicer <lb/>Arietinum; the palm of the hand; a measure, <i>= <lb/>hasta-bheda,</i> a cubit; a bank or shore; (<i>a1</i>), f. <lb/>Convolvulus Turpethum; Arabian jasmine; small <lb/>cardamoms; a form of Durga1; (<i>i1</i>), f. Convolvulus <lb/>Turpethum; small cardamoms; [cf. <i>kara1la-tri- <lb/>put2a1.</i>] <i>--Triput2aka, as, a1, am,</i> triangular; (<i>as</i>), <lb/>m. a triangle; a species of pulse. <i>--Triput2a1-pu1ja1- <lb/>yantra, am,</i> n., N. of a kind of mystical diagram <lb/>described in the Tantra-sa1ra by Kr2ishn2a1nanda. <i>--Tri- <lb/>put2a1-mantra, a1s,</i> m. pl., N. of a chapter of the Tan- <lb/>tra-sa1ra. <i>--Triput2a1-stotra, am,</i> n., N. of a chapter <lb/>of the Tantra-sa1ra. <i>--Triput2in, i1,</i> m. or <i>triput2i1- <lb/>phala, as,</i> m. the castor-oil plant, Ricinus Com- <lb/>munis. <i>--Tri-pun2d2ra</i> or <i>tri-pun2d2hra</i> or <i>tri- <lb/>pun2d2raka, am,</i> n. a mark consisting of three lines <lb/>on the forehead, the back, heart, and shoulders, or <lb/>three curved horizontal marks made across the fore- <lb/>head with cow-dung, ashes, &amp;c., which are worn <lb/>especially by the followers of S4iva or S4akti, and are <lb/>indispensable in proceeding to worship the former; <lb/>(<i>as, a1, am</i>), having three horizontal marks. <i>--Tri- <lb/>pur,</i> f. (in pl. <i>tri-puras</i>) <i>= tri-pura. --Tri-pura, <lb/>am,</i> n. three strong cities collectively, a triple forti- <lb/>fication; (in epic poetry) three strong cities of gold, <lb/>silver, and iron, in the sky, air, and earth, built by <lb/>Maya for a celebrated Asura or demon, and burnt by <lb/>S4iva; (<i>as</i>), m., N. of the above Asura and king of <lb/>Tri-pura; a form of S4iva; (<i>a1</i>), f., N. of a town; a <lb/>form of Durga1 <i>(= tri-put2a1 ?); (i1),</i> f., N. of a town, <lb/><i>= c4edi-nagari1;</i> N. of a country to the south-east <lb/>of Madhya-des4a, the modern Tipparah; (<i>a1</i> or <i>i1?</i>), <lb/>N. of an Upanishad. <i>--Tripura-kuma1ra, as,</i> m., <lb/>N. of a pupil of S4an4kara1c4a1rya mentioned in the <lb/>S4an4kara-vijaya by Ananta1nanda-giri. <i>--Tripura- <lb/>ghna, as,</i> or <i>tripura-jit, t,</i> or <i>tripura-dahana,</i> or <lb/><i>tripura-da1ha, as,</i> m., N. of S4iva as destroyer <lb/>of Tri-pura. <i>--Tripura-da1ha, as,</i> m. ‘burning of <lb/>Tri-pura,’ N. of the 3rd chapter of the Pa1ta1la- <lb/>khan2d2a of the Padma-Pura1n2a. <i>--Tripura-bhairavi1,</i> <lb/>f. a form of Durga1. <i>--Tripura-mallika1,</i> f. a medicinal <lb/>plant, apparently a kind of jasmine; [cf. <i>tri-put2a1.</i>] <lb/><i>--Tripura-vadha, as,</i> m. ‘slaughter of Tri-pura,’ <lb/>N. of the 7th chapter of the Uttara-khan2d2a of the <lb/>S4iva-Pura1n2a. <i>--Tripura-vijaya, as,</i> m. ‘conquest <lb/>of Tri-pura,’ N. of the 70th chapter of the Lin4ga- <lb/>Pura1n2a. <i>--Tripura-hara, as,</i> m., N. of the 71st <lb/>chapter of the Lin4ga-Pura1n2a. <i>--Tripura1dha1ran2a- <lb/>yantra (ºna-a1dhº), am,</i> n., N. of a mystical dia- <lb/>gram given in the Tantra-sa1ra. <i>--Tripura1dhipati <lb/>(ºra-adhº), is,</i> m., N. of Maya, builder of the city of <lb/>Tri-pura. <i>--Tripura1ntaka</i> or <i>tripura1nta-kara (ºra- <lb/>anº), as,</i> m., N. of S4iva as destroyer of Tri-pura. [Page0390-b+ 81] <lb/><i>--Tripura1-nya1sa, as,</i> m., N. of a chapter of the <lb/>Tantra-sa1ra. <i>--Tripura1-bhairavi1,</i> f. a form of <lb/>Durga1. <i>--Tripura1bhairavi1-pu1ja1-yantra, am,</i> n., <lb/>N. of a mystical diagram given in the Tantra-sa1ra. <lb/><i>--Tripura1ri (ºra-arº), is,</i> m. ‘the enemy of Tri- <lb/>pura,’ a N. of S4iva. <i>--Tripura1rn2ava (ºra-arº), as,</i> <lb/>m., N. of a literary work. <i>--Tripura1rdana (ºra-arº), <lb/>as,</i> m. <i>= tripura1ntaka. --Tripuri1-prakaran2a, <lb/>am,</i> n., N. of a work, probably by San4kara, con- <lb/>taining the elements of the Veda1nta phil. <i>--Tri- <lb/>purusha, as, a1, am,</i> having the length of three <lb/>men; having three assistants; (<i>am</i>), ind. through <lb/>three males, i. e. through three generations of men, <lb/>or father, grandfather, and great-grandfather. <i>--Tri- <lb/>purusha1gata (ºsha-a1gº), as, a1, am,</i> inherited through <lb/>three generations. <i>--Tripures4a (ºra-i1s4º), as,</i> m. <lb/>‘lord of Tri-pura,’ N. of S4iva. <i>--Tripures4a1dri (ºs4a- <lb/>adº), is,</i> m., N. of a mountain. <i>--Tripures4vara <lb/>(ºra-i1s4º),</i> N. of a town or district, or of a sacred <lb/>place. <i>--Tripuropa1khya1na (ºra1-upº), am,</i> n. ‘the <lb/>story of Tri-pura,’ N. of the 52-54th chapters of the <lb/>Jn3a1na-khan2d2a or second part of the S4iva-Pura1n2a. <lb/><i>--Tri-pusha1,</i> f. Convolvulus Turpethum, <i>= kr2ishn2a- <lb/>tri-vr2it;</i> [cf. <i>tri-put2a1.</i>] <i>--Tri-pushkara, a1s,</i> m. pl. <lb/>‘the three lakes,’ N. of certain holy bathing-places; <lb/>(<i>as, a1, am</i>), decorated with three lotus flowers. <i>--Tri- <lb/>pr2isht2ha, as,</i> m. (with Jainas) N. of the first of the <lb/>black Va1su-devas; a N. of Vishn2u, as ‘living above <lb/>the three worlds,’ or as ‘existing independently of the <lb/>three qualities of nature;’ epithet of the Soma, as hav- <lb/>ing three elevations or surfaces, found in three places (?), <lb/>having three hymns (?), having three vessels (?), hav- <lb/>ing three waters (used in its preparation ?), having <lb/>three oblations (?), having three filtering cloths (?), <lb/>or press, filter, and vessel for holding the Soma (?). <lb/>(The above are the conjectures of various scholars, but <lb/>according to Sa1y. the word means) ‘mixed with <lb/>cream, thickened with milk,’ &amp;c.; (<i>am</i>), n. the <lb/>highest part of the three heavens, the highest heaven. <lb/><i>--Tri-paurusha, as, i1, am,</i> extending or be- <lb/>longing to three persons or three generations of <lb/>men; offered to three (as the funeral cake &amp;c.), <lb/>inherited from three (as an estate &amp;c.); [cf. <i>trai- <lb/>purusha.</i>] <i>--Tri-prasruta, as, a1, am,</i> epithet of a <lb/>rutting elephant, i. e. ‘having three streams of fluid <lb/>flowing from the forehead.’ <i>--Tri-plaksha, a1s,</i> m. <lb/>pl. ‘the three fig-trees,’ a place near the Yamuna1 in <lb/>the neighbourhood of which the Dr2ishad-vati1 dis- <lb/>appears. <i>--Tri-phala, as, a1, am,</i> having three fruits; <lb/>(<i>a1</i>), f. the three myrobalans, the fruits of Terminalia <lb/>Chebula, T. Bellerica, and Phyllanthus Emblica; <lb/>the three fragrant fruits, nutmeg, areca-nut, and <lb/>cloves; the three sweet fruits, grape, pomegranate, <lb/>and date. <i>--Triphala1di-varga (ºla-a1dº), as,</i> m., <lb/>N. of a chapter of the S4abda-c4andrika1 or medical <lb/>lexicon by C4akra-pa1n2i-datta. <i>--Tri-bandhana, as,</i> <lb/>m., N. of the son of Arun2a and father of Tri-s4an4ku. <lb/><i>--Tri-bandhu, us,</i> m. the friend of the three <lb/>worlds or regions; (Sa1y.) binding together or sup- <lb/>porting the three worlds, (said of Indra.) <i>--Tri- <lb/>bandhura, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. having three uneven <lb/>poles or seats, (said of the chariot of the As4vins.) <lb/><i>--Tri-barhis, is, is, is,</i> Ved. having three seats of <lb/>sacrificial grass. <i>--Tri-bali1,</i> f. three folds of skin or <lb/>corrugations over the navel (of a woman; this <lb/>peculiarity is regarded as a beauty); the anus. <lb/><i>--Tri-bali1ka, as,</i> m., N. of Ra1ma, ‘having three <lb/>folds in the neck;’ (<i>am</i>), n. the anus. <i>--Tri-ba1hu, <lb/>us, us, u,</i> ‘three-armed,’ epithet of a kind of <lb/>spirit or demon; (<i>us</i>), m. a technical term in <lb/>fighting. <i>--Tri-buli1ka, am,</i> n. the anus. <i>--Tri-bha, <lb/>am,</i> n. three signs of the zodiac, the quadrant of a <lb/>circle, ninety degrees; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), containing three <lb/>signs of the zodiac. <i>--Tri-bhan4ga, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>having three curves or bends (as have many images <lb/>of Kr2ishn2a); (<i>i1</i>), f., N. of a metre consisting of <lb/>4 × 32 syllabic instants. <i>--Tribha-ji1va1,</i> f. and <i>tri- <lb/>bha-jya1,</i> f. <i>= tri-ji1va1</i> and <i>tri-jya1. --Tri-bhan2d2i1,</i> <lb/>f. Convolvulus Turpethum. <i>--Tri-bhadra, am,</i> n. <lb/>copulation, cohabitation. <i>--Tribha-maurvika1,</i> f. <i>= <lb/>tri-jya1. --Tri-bha1ga, as,</i> m. the third part; the [Page0390-c+ 81] <lb/>third part of a sign of the zodiac. <i>--Tri-bha1nu, us,</i> <lb/>m., N. of a descendant of Yaya1ti and father of <lb/>Karan-dhama. <i>--Tri-bha1shya-ratna, am,</i> n., N. of <lb/>a commentary on the Taittiri1ya-Pra1tis4a1khya. <i>--Tri- <lb/>bhukti = ti1ra-bhukti (?) . --Tri-bhuj, k, k, k,</i> Ved. <lb/>threefold. <i>--Tri-bhuja, as, a1, am,</i> having three arms, <lb/>triangular; (<i>as</i>), m. a triangle. <i>--Tri-bhuvana, am,</i> <lb/>n. the three worlds, i. e. sky, atmosphere, and earth, <lb/>or heaven, earth, and the lower region; (<i>as</i>), m., <lb/>N. of a prince. <i>--Tribhuvana-guru, us,</i> m. ‘master <lb/>of the three worlds,’ epithet of S4iva. <i>--Tribhuva- <lb/>na-pati, is,</i> m. ‘lord of the three worlds,’ epithet of <lb/>Vishn2u. <i>--Tribhuvanes4vara (ºna-i1s4º), as,</i> m. ‘lord <lb/>of the three worlds,’ epithet of Indra. <i>--Tribhu- <lb/>vanes4vara-lin4ga, am,</i> n., N. of a Lin4ga temple. <lb/><i>--Tribhona-lagna (ºbha-u1nº), am,</i> n. that part of <lb/>the ecliptic which does not reach the eastern point <lb/>by three signs or ninety degrees, i. e. the highest <lb/>point of the ecliptic above the horizon. <i>--Tri- <lb/>man2d2ala1,</i> f., scil. <i>lu1ta1,</i> a kind of poisonous spider. <lb/><i>--Tri-mada, as, am,</i> m. n. (?) the three narcotic <lb/>plants, Musta1, C4itraka, Vid2an4ga; the threefold illusion. <lb/><i>--Tri-madhu, u,</i> n. the three sweet substances, <lb/>sugar, honey, and ghee; (<i>us</i>), m. one who knows or <lb/>recites the three verses of R2ig-veda 1. 90, 6-8, which <lb/>begin with <i>madhu. --Tri-madhura, am,</i> n. the <lb/>three sweet substances, sugar, honey, and ghee. <lb/><i>--Tri-malla,</i> N. of a place of pilgrimage. <i>--Tri- <lb/>ma1tr2i, ta1,</i> m., Ved. ‘having three mothers;’ (Sa1y.) the <lb/>maker or creator of the three worlds. <i>--Tri-ma1rga,</i> <lb/>(at the beginning of a comp.) the three paths; <lb/>(<i>i1</i>), f. three ways or paths; the meeting of three <lb/>roads; [cf. <i>tri-patha.</i>] <i>--Trima1rga-ga1,</i> f. flowing <lb/>by three ways; [cf. <i>tripatha-ga1.</i>] <i>--Tri-mukut2a, <lb/>as,</i> m. a mountain with three peaks; N. of a <lb/>mountain, <i>= tri-ku1t2a. --Tri-mukha, as, i1, am,</i> <lb/>three-faced, having three faces, having three mouths; <lb/>(<i>as</i>), m., N. of the third Arhat of the present Ava- <lb/>sarpin2i1; (<i>a1</i>), f. an epithet of Ma1ya1 or the mother of <lb/>S4a1kya-muni. <i>--Tri-muni,</i> ind. produced by the <lb/>three Munis or sages, (as the grammar of Pa1n2ini, <lb/>Ka1tya1yana, and Patan3jali.) <i>--Tri-mu1rti, is, is, i,</i> <lb/>having or assuming three forms or shapes, (as Brahma1, <lb/>Vishn2u, and S4iva); (<i>is</i>), m. a Buddha, a Jina; (<i>is</i>), <lb/>f. (?) the Hindu1 triad, the united form of the above <lb/>three gods. <i>--Tri-mu1rdha, as, a1, am,</i> three-headed. <lb/><i>--Tri-mu1rdhan, a1,</i> m. ‘three-headed,’ N. of a <lb/>Ra1kshasa. <i>--Triy-ambaka, as,</i> m. <i>= try-ambaka,</i> <lb/>‘triocular,’ ‘three-eyed,’ N. of S4iva. <i>--Tri-yava, as, a1, <lb/>am,</i> containing or weighing three barleycorns; (<i>am</i>), <lb/>n. a retti (<i>= raktika</i>) or weight of three barley- <lb/>corns, <i>= kr2ishn2ala. --Triy-avi = try-avi. --Tri- <lb/>yasht2i, is,</i> m. a species of plant, <i>= kshetra-parpat2i1. <lb/>--Tri-ya1na, am,</i> n. (with Buddhists) the three <lb/>vehicles (leading to welfare). <i>--Tri-ya1ma, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>containing (as the night) three Ya1mas or watches, <lb/>i. e. about nine hours; (<i>a1</i>), f. night, (<i>ahas-triya1- <lb/>mam,</i> day and night); turmeric; a convolvulus with <lb/>dark flowers; the Indigo plant; the river Yamuna1. <lb/><i>--Tri-ya1maka, am,</i> n. sin (‘the impeder of the <lb/>three objects of life?’). <i>--Tri-yuga, am,</i> n. a space <lb/>of time containing three periods or ages; (<i>as</i>), m. <lb/>‘appearing in the three Yugas,’ epithet of Kr2ishn2a. <lb/><i>--Tri-yoni, is,</i> f. a lawsuit in which a person <lb/>engages from anger, covetousness, or infatuation. <lb/><i>--Triyyr2ic4a = try-r2ic4a = tr2ic4a,</i> a strophe consist- <lb/>ing of three verses. <i>--Tri-ratna, am,</i> n. the three <lb/>gems, viz. Buddha, the law, and the congregation. <lb/><i>--Tri-rasaka, am,</i> n. a spirituous liquor (‘having <lb/>a triple flavour’). <i>--Tri-ra1tra, am,</i> n. three nights <lb/>collectively, or the duration of three nights or days; <lb/>(<i>am</i>), ind. for three nights or days, during three <lb/>days; (<i>a1t</i> or <i>en2a</i>), ind. after three days; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), <lb/>lasting three days; (<i>as</i>), m. a festival which lasts <lb/>three days; [cf. <i>try-aha.</i>] <i>--Tri-ra1s4i-pa, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>governing three signs of the zodiac. <i>--Tri-ru1pa, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> of three colours. <i>--Tri-rekha, as,</i> m. <lb/>‘having three lines,’ a conch, a muscle-shell, a shell <lb/>marked with three lines. <i>--Tri-lavan2a, am,</i> n. the <lb/>three salts, <i>= tri-pat2u,</i> q. v. <i>--Tri-lin4ga, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>possessing the three Gun2as; having three genders, [Page0391-a+ 81] <lb/>(often = ‘an adjective’); the Sanskr2it form for Telinga <lb/>(called so fr. three Lin4gas). <i>--Tri-lin4gaka, as,</i> &amp;c., <lb/>having three genders, an adjective. <i>--Tri-lin4gi1,</i> <lb/>f. the three grammatical genders. <i>--Tri-loka, am,</i> n. <lb/>the three worlds, i. e. sky, atmosphere, and earth, or <lb/>heaven, earth, and the lower region; (<i>as</i>), m. an <lb/>inhabitant of the three worlds; (<i>i1</i>), f. the universe, <lb/>the aggregate of the three worlds. <i>--Triloka-na1tha, <lb/>as,</i> m. ‘lord of the three worlds,’ an epithet of <lb/>Indra. <i>--Triloka-rakshin, i1,</i> m. guardian of the <lb/>three worlds. <i>--Triloka1tman (ºka-a1tº), a1,</i> m. ‘soul <lb/>of the three worlds,’ epithet of S4iva. <i>--Triloki1- <lb/>na1tha, as,</i> m. an epithet of Vishn2u. <i>--Trilokes4a <lb/>(ºka-i1s4º), as,</i> m. ‘lord of the three worlds,’ an <lb/>epithet of the Sun. <i>--Tri-loc4ana, as, a1</i> or <i>i1, am,</i> ‘tri- <lb/>ocular,’ ‘three-eyed,’ epithet of S4iva; (<i>as</i>), m., N. of <lb/>a poet; of a grammarian; of a prince &amp;c.; (<i>a1</i>), f. <lb/>a disloyal wife, unchaste woman; (with Buddhists) <lb/>N. of a deity; (<i>i1</i>), f. an epithet of Durga1. <i>--Tri- <lb/>loc4ana-ti1rtha, am,</i> n., N. of a Ti1rtha. <i>--Triloc4ana- <lb/>da1sa, as,</i> m., N. of a grammarian. <i>--Triloc4ane- <lb/>s4vara-ti1rtha (ºna-i1s4º), am,</i> n., N. of a Ti1rtha. <lb/><i>--Tri-lohaka, am,</i> n. the three metals, i. e. gold, <lb/>silver, and copper. <i>--Tri-lauha, as, i1, am,</i> made of <lb/>the above three metals. <i>--Tri-vat, a1n, ati1, at,</i> con- <lb/>taining the word <i>tri. --Tri-vatsa, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. <lb/>three years old (as an ox or cow). <i>--Tri-vandhura,</i> <lb/>see <i>tri-bandhura. --Tri-varga, as,</i> m. an aggreagate <lb/>of three things or substances &amp;c.; the three objects <lb/>or pursuits of life, viz. religion or virtue (<i>dharma</i>), <lb/>pleasure (<i>ka1ma</i>), and wealth (<i>artha</i>); the three <lb/>conditions of a king or kingdom, viz. progress <lb/>(<i>vr2iddhi</i>), remaining stationary (<i>stha1na</i>), and de- <lb/>cline (<i>kshaya</i>); the three qualities of nature, viz. <lb/><i>sat-tva, rajas,</i> and <i>tamas,</i> see under <i>gun2a;</i> the <lb/>three higher castes or tribes; the three myrobalans; <lb/>the three spices &amp;c.; propriety, good behaviour. <lb/><i>--Trivarga-c4intana, am,</i> n., N. of a chapter of <lb/>the Pura1n2a-sarva-sva. <i>--Trivarga-pa1ri1n2a, as, a1, <lb/>am,</i> having passed through the three conditions or <lb/>attained the three objects of life. <i>--Tri-varn2a, am,</i> n. <lb/>three colours; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), three-coloured (Ved.). <lb/><i>--Tri-varn2aka, am,</i> n. a kind of plant, <i>= go-kshu- <lb/>raka;</i> the three myrobalans [cf. <i>tri-phala1</i>]; the three <lb/>spices; [cf. <i>tri-kat2u.</i>] <i>--Trivarn2a-kr2it, t,</i> m. the <lb/>chameleon. <i>--Tri-vartu, us, us, u,</i> Ved. threefold; <lb/>[cf. <i>tri-vr2it.</i>] <i>--Trivartma-ga1,</i> f. ‘flowing by three <lb/>paths,’ an epithet of the Gan4ga1; [cf. <i>tripatha-ga1.</i>] <lb/><i>--Tri-vartman, a,</i> n. three paths; (<i>a1, a1, a</i>), going <lb/>by three paths (Ved.). <i>--Tri-varsha, am,</i> n. a period <lb/>of three years; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), three years old. <i>--Tri- <lb/>varshika1,</i> f. a three-year-old heifer. <i>--Tri-varshi1ya, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> triennial, lasting for three years, used for <lb/>three years. <i>--Tri-vali, i1,</i> n. f. the three folds or <lb/>wrinkles across the belly; [cf. <i>tri-bali1.</i>] <i>--Tri- <lb/>va1ra, as,</i> m., N. of a son of Garud2a; (<i>am</i>), ind. <lb/>three times, thrice. <i>--Tri-vikrama, am,</i> n. the <lb/>three steps (of Vishn2u), three strides; (<i>as</i>), m. <lb/>‘one who makes three steps or strides,’ an epithet <lb/>of Vishn2u, who paced the three worlds in three <lb/>steps in his Va1mana or dwarf Avata1r, see <i>bali;</i> N. <lb/>of a Bra1hman; of an astronomer; of a jurist; of a <lb/>medical author. <i>--Trivikrama-ti1rtha, am,</i> n., N. <lb/>of a Ti1rtha. <i>--Trivikrama-deva, as,</i> m., N. of an <lb/>author. <i>--Trivikrama-bhat2t2a, as,</i> m., N. of the <lb/>author of the Damayanti1-katha1. <i>--Trivikrama1c4a1rya <lb/>(ºma-a1c4º), as,</i> m., N. of an astronomer. <i>--Tri- <lb/>vidya, as,</i> m. an epithet of S4iva, ‘familiar with or <lb/>containing the three Vedas;’ (<i>a1</i>), f. three branches <lb/>of knowledge, especially that of the three Vedas. <lb/><i>--Tri-vidha, as, a1, am,</i> of three kinds, threefold, <lb/>triple, in three ways. <i>--Tri-vidha1,</i> ind. (?), in three <lb/>parts, triply (?). <i>--Tri-vinata, as, a1, am,</i> bowing <lb/>in the presence of three, viz. gods, Bra1hmans, and <lb/>preceptors; bent in three places, curved in three <lb/>parts of the body (?). <i>--Tri-visht2apa, am,</i> n. <i>= tri- <lb/>pisht2apa,</i> the world of Indra, i. e. heaven or paradise; <lb/>the three worlds. <i>--Trivisht2apa-sad, t,</i> m. an in- <lb/>habitant of heaven, a deity. <i>--Tri-vista, as, a1, am, <lb/>= tri-vaistika,</i> worth three Vistas. <i>--Tri-vi1ja, as,</i> <lb/>m. a kind of grain; [cf. <i>s4ya1ma1ka.</i>] <i>--Tri-vr2it, [Page0391-b+ 81] <lb/>t, t, t,</i> threefold, triple, tri-form; consisting of three <lb/>parts or folds &amp;c.; (with <i>stoma</i>) a threefold hymn <lb/>of praise, (i. e. a particular recitation, in which first <lb/>the first three R2iks of each Tr2ic4a of the eleventh <lb/>hymn of the ninth Man2d2ala of the R2ig-veda are sung <lb/>together, then the second R2iks, and lastly the third; <lb/>hence this Stoma consists of 3 × 3 or 9 verses); <lb/>connected with the Trivr2it-stoma; (<i>t</i>), m. a triple <lb/>cord consisting of three strings; a girdle &amp;c. of <lb/>three strings; an amulet of three strings; (<i>t</i>), f. a <lb/>plant of valuable purgative properties, commonly <lb/>called Te7ori, and distinguished into two species, <lb/>white and black (Convolvulus Turpethum); also <lb/>called <i>tri-vr2ita1;</i> [cf. <i>try-a1vr2it.</i>] <i>--Tri-vr2ita,</i> f.; see <lb/>the preceding. <i>--Trivr2it-karan2a, as, i1, am,</i> com- <lb/>bining three things; (<i>am</i>), n. making a com- <lb/>bination of three things; combining earth, water, <lb/>and fire, in the proportion of half of one with a <lb/>quarter of each of the others. <i>--Tri-vr2itti, is,</i> f. <lb/>truth (?); [cf. <i>try-akshara.</i>] <i>--Trivr2it-parn2i1,</i> f., <lb/>N. of a pot-herb, Hincha Repens; [cf. <i>hila-moc4i.</i>] <lb/><i>--Tri-vr2inta, as,</i> m. (?) the plant Butea Frondosa. <lb/><i>--Trivr2intika1,</i> f. the plant Ipomœa Turpethum. <lb/><i>--Tri-vr2isha, as,</i> m., N. of a Muni; [cf. the next.] <lb/><i>--Tri-vr2ishan, a1,</i> m., N. of the father of Try-arun2a <lb/>[cf. <i>trai-vr2ishn2a</i>]; N. of the Vya1sa of the twelfth <lb/>Dva1para. <i>--Tri-ven2i1,</i> f. ‘triple-braid,’ the place (now <lb/>called Allahabad) where the Gan4ga1 joins with the <lb/>Yamuna1 or Jumna1 and is supposed to receive under- <lb/>ground the Sarasvati1; N. of the Gan4ga1. <i>--Tri-ven2u, <lb/>us,</i> m. a particular part of a carriage; (<i>us, us, u</i>), <lb/>epithet of a carriage, (according to some) furnished <lb/>with three banners. <i>--Tri-veda,</i> (at the beginning of <lb/>a comp.) the three Vedas, viz. R2ig, Yajus, and <lb/>Sa1man; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), familiar with the three Vedas. <lb/><i>--Tri-vedin, i1, ini1, i,</i> familiar or acquainted with <lb/>the three Vedas. <i>--Tri-vedi1,</i> f. the three Vedas <lb/>collectively. <i>--Tri-vela1,</i> f. the plant Ipomœa Tur- <lb/>pethum. <i>--Tri-s4akti, is,</i> f., N. of a female deity, <lb/><i>= tri-kala1. --Tri-s4an4ku, us,</i> m., N. of a sage; N. <lb/>of a prince of the solar race, king of Ayodhya1, <lb/>(according to the Ra1ma1yan2a he was a son of Pr2ithu, <lb/>and was a pious prince who aspired to celebrate a <lb/>great sacrifice whereby to ascend to heaven in his <lb/>mortal body; he first requested the sage Vasisht2ha <lb/>to officiate for him, but being refused he then <lb/>applied to the sage's hundred sons, by whom he was <lb/>cursed and degraded to the condition of a C4a1n2d2a1la; <lb/>in this emergency he had recourse to Vis4va1-mitra, <lb/>who undertook the sacrifice and invited all the gods <lb/>to be present; they, however, declined, upon which <lb/>the enraged Vis4va1-mitra, by his own power, trans- <lb/>ported Tri-s4an4ku to the skies, whither he had no <lb/>sooner arrived than he was hurled down again head- <lb/>foremost by the gods; but, being arrested in his <lb/>downward course by Vis4va1-mitra, remained suspended <lb/>with his head towards the earth, forming a constella- <lb/>tion in the southern hemisphere: according to the <lb/>Hari-van6s4a and Va1yu-Pura1n2a he was a son of Tray- <lb/>ya1run2a: according to the Bha1gavata-Pura1n2a, a son <lb/>of Tri-bandhana: and he is sometimes described as <lb/>a wicked prince, guilty of three S4an4kus or heinous <lb/>crimes); a cat, the civet-cat; a bird, the C4a1taka, <lb/>Cuculus Melanoleucos; a grasshopper; a fire-fly. <lb/><i>--Tris4an4ku-ja, as,</i> m. ‘the son of Tri-s4an4ku,’ epithet <lb/>of Hari-s4c4andra. <i>--Tris4an4ku-ya1jin, i1,</i> m. ‘sacrificing <lb/>for Tri-s4an4ku,’ epithet of Vis4va1-mitra. <i>--Tri-s4ata, <lb/>am,</i> n., 103, 300; (<i>as, i1, am</i>), the 300th; con- <lb/>sisting of 300; (<i>a1s</i>), m. pl., 300. <i>--Tri-s4ataka, <lb/>as, ika1, am,</i> consisting of 300. <i>--Tris4ata-tama, <lb/>as, i1, am,</i> the 300th; the 103rd. <i>--Tri-s4ati1,</i> f. the <lb/>aggregate of 300 (e. g. <i>pas4u1na1m2 tri-s4ati1,</i> 300 <lb/>cattle). <i>--Tri-s4aran2a, am,</i> n. (with Buddhists) the <lb/>three places of refuge, Buddha, the Law, and the <lb/>Assembly; (<i>as</i>), m. a Buddha. <i>--Tri-s4arkara1,</i> f. <lb/>three kinds of sugar, viz. <i>gud2otpanna1, himottha1,</i> <lb/>and <i>madhura1;</i> [cf. <i>tri-sita1.</i>] <i>--Tri-s4ala1,</i> f., N. of the <lb/>mother of the twenty-fourth Arhat of the present Ava- <lb/>sarpin2i1. <i>--Tris4ala1ka1-purusha-c4arita, am,</i> n., N. of <lb/>a work by Hema-c4andra. <i>--Tri-s4as,</i> ind. by threes, <lb/>by three at a time. <i>--Tri-s4a1kha, as, i1, am,</i> having [Page0391-c+ 81] <lb/>three branches. <i>--Tris4a1kha-pattra, as,</i> m. the plant <lb/>Ægle Marmelos. <i>--Tri-s4a1n2a, as, i1, am,</i> worth <lb/>three S4a1n2as. <i>--Tri-s4a1nu, us,</i> m. a various reading <lb/>for <i>tri-bha1nu. --Tri-s4a1la, as, a1, am,</i> or <i>tri- <lb/>s4a1laka, as, a1, am,</i> consisting of three halls or <lb/>rooms; (<i>am</i>), n. a house with three halls. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4ikha, as, a1, am,</i> three-crested, three-headed, having <lb/>the shape of a trident; (<i>as</i>), m. the plant Ægle <lb/>Marmelos; the son of Ra1van2a, a demon with three <lb/>heads; N. of Indra in the Manv-antara of Ta1masa; <lb/>(<i>i1</i>), f., N. of an Upanishad; (<i>am</i>), n. a trident, a <lb/>three-pronged spear; a crest, a tiara with three <lb/>points. <i>--Tri-s4ikhara, as, a1, am,</i> having three tops <lb/>or peaks; (<i>as</i>), m. (with <i>s4aila</i>) N. of a mountain. <lb/><i>--Tris4ikhi-dala1,</i> f. a kind of bulbous plant. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4ikhin, i1, ini1, i,</i> three-crested, three-headed. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4ira, as, a1, am,</i> having three points; (<i>as</i>), m., N. <lb/>of a Ra1kshasa; (<i>a1</i>), f. the root of Bignonia Suave- <lb/>olens. <i>--Tri-s4iras, a1s, a1s, as,</i> three-headed, having <lb/>three points or tops; (<i>a1s</i>), m. epithet of Tva1sht2ra <lb/>Vis4va-ru1pa; Fever personified as a demon with three <lb/>heads [cf. <i>tri-pad</i> and <i>tri-pa1d</i>]; N. of an Asura <lb/>killed by Vishn2u; N. of a Ra1kshasa killed by <lb/>Ra1ma; an epithet of Kuvera. <i>--Tri-s4i1rsha, as, a1, <lb/>am,</i> ‘three-headed,’ an epithet of S4iva. <i>--Tri-s4i1r- <lb/>shaka, as, a1, am,</i> three-headed; (<i>am</i>), n. a tri- <lb/>dent, a three-pointed or three-pronged spear. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4i1rshan, a1, a1, a,</i> Ved. three-headed. <i>--Tri-s4ukra, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> Ved. white or bright in three places. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4ukriya, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. triply illuminated. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4uc4, k, k, k,</i> Ved. triply shining or splendid, shining in <lb/>three ways. <i>--Tri-s4u1la, am,</i> n. a trident, a three- <lb/>pointed pike or spear, especially the weapon of S4iva; <lb/>(<i>as, a1, am</i>), ‘bearing the trident,’ epithet of S4iva; <lb/>N. of a mountain. <i>--Tris4u1la-kha1ta, am,</i> n., N. <lb/>of a Ti1rtha, (‘digged with the trident.’) <i>--Tris4u1la- <lb/>gan4ga1,</i> f., N. of a river. <i>--Tris4u1la1n4ka (ºla-an4º), as,</i> <lb/>m. ‘trident-marked,’ a N. of S4iva; of a teacher. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4u1lin, i1, ini1, i,</i> ‘armed with the trident;’ (<i>i1</i>), m. <lb/>epithet of S4iva; (<i>ini1</i>), f. epithet of Durga1. <i>--Tri- <lb/>s4r2in4ga, as, a1, am,</i> having three horns or peaks; <lb/>(<i>as</i>), m. a hill with three peaks; N. of a mountain; <lb/>a triangle. <i>--Tris4r2in4gin, i1, in2i1, i,</i> having three <lb/>horns; (<i>i1</i>), m. a sort of fish, commonly Rohi, <lb/>Cyprinus Rohita. <i>--Tri-s4oka, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. <i>= <lb/>tri-s4uc4 (?) ; (as),</i> m., N. of a R2ishi. <i>--Tri-sham2- <lb/>yukta, as, a1, am</i> (for <i>tri-samº),</i> triply connected. <lb/><i>--Tri-sham2vatsara, as, a1, am</i> (for <i>tri-samº),</i> <lb/>lasting three years. <i>--Tri-shatya, as, a1, am</i> (for <i>tri- <lb/>satya</i>), Ved. trebly true (in thought, word, and deed). <lb/><i>--Tri-shadhastha, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. being in three <lb/>places. <i>--Tri-shandhi, is, is, i</i> (for <i>tri-sanº),</i> Ved. <lb/>composed of three parts or members; (<i>is</i>), m., N. <lb/>of a demon in the Atharva-veda, generally associated <lb/>with Arbudi; (<i>i1</i>), n., N. of a Sa1man. <i>--Tri-shapta</i> <lb/>or <i>tri-sapta</i> (fr. <i>tri+saptan</i>), Ved. three times <lb/>seven, twenty-one; an indefinite number. <i>--Tri- <lb/>shapti1ya, as,</i> m. adj., N. of the first verse of the <lb/>Atharva-veda, beginning with the words <i>ye tri- <lb/>shapta1s,</i> &amp;c. <i>--Tri-shavan2a</i> or <i>tri-savana, as, a1, <lb/>am,</i> containing three oblations; (<i>as</i>), m., N. of an <lb/>ancient sage; <i>tri-shavan2am</i> or <i>trishavan2a-sna1nam,</i> <lb/>the three ablutions to be performed daily, i. e. at dawn, <lb/>noon, and sunset. <i>--Trishavan2a-sna1yin, i1,</i> m. a <lb/>man performing regularly the prescribed ablutions <lb/>morning, noon, and evening. <i>--Trishasht2a, as, i1, <lb/>am,</i> the sixty-third. <i>--Tri-shasht2i, is,</i> m. sixty- <lb/>three; [cf. <i>trayah2-shasht2i.</i>] <i>--Trishasht2i-tama, <lb/>as, i1, am,</i> the sixty-third. <i>--Trishasht2i-dha1,</i> ind. <lb/>in sixty-three parts, sixty-three-fold. <i>--Trishasht2i- <lb/>s4ala1ka1purusha-c4arita, am,</i> n., N. of a work. <lb/><i>--Trisht2up-c4handas, a1s, a1s, as,</i> Ved. having the <lb/>metre Tri-sht2ubh. <i>--Tri-sht2ubh, p,</i> f. (for <i>tri-stubh</i> <lb/>fr. <i>tri+stubh,</i> to praise; or possibly the word may <lb/>come fr. <i>stubh,</i> to stop, because the voice is obliged <lb/>to pause three times; according to Ya1ska, the prefix <lb/><i>tri</i> may be fr. rt. <i>tr2i1,</i> to denote the rapidity of <lb/>the metre, cf. <i>jagati1;</i> or fr. <i>tri,</i> three, <i>+stubh,</i> to <lb/>praise, because the metre is in praise of the <i>vajra</i> <lb/>or thunderbolt, which has three edges); N. of a <lb/>Vedic metre consisting of four Pa1das of eleven [Page0392-a+ 81] <lb/>syllables each; (in the later metrical system) N. of <lb/>every metre consisting of four times eleven syllables <lb/>(e. g. the Indra-vajra1 and Upendra-vajra1 metres); [cf. <lb/><i>traisht2ubha.</i>] <i>--Tri-sht2oma, as, a1, am</i> (for <i>tri- <lb/>stoma</i>), Ved. containing three Stomas; (<i>as</i>), m., N. of <lb/>an Eka1ha. <i>--Tri-sht2ha, as, a1, am</i> (for <i>tri-stha</i>), Ved. <lb/>standing on three (wheels), situated in three places; <lb/>(<i>as</i>), m., N. of a man. <i>--Tri-sht2hin, i1, ini1, i</i> (for <i>tri- <lb/>sthin</i>), Ved. standing on triply divided ground. <i>--Tri- <lb/>sam2vatsara,</i> see under <i>tri-sham2vatsara. --Tri- <lb/>satya,</i> see under <i>tri-shatya. --Tri-sandhi, is, is, i,</i> <lb/>see <i>tri-shandhi; (is),</i> f. a kind of mallow. <i>--Tri- <lb/>sandhika, as, a1, am,</i> occurring or happening at the <lb/>three periods or divisions of the day, (probably a <lb/>wrong reading for <i>trisandhyika.</i>) <i>--Tri-sandhya, <lb/>am,</i> n. the three periods or divisions of the day, viz. <lb/>dawn, noon, and evening or sunset; (<i>a1</i>), f., N. of a <lb/>goddess; a form of Durga1; a kind of mallow; (<i>a1</i> <lb/>or <i>i1</i>), f. the three periods of the day; (<i>am</i>), ind. <lb/>at the time of the three Sandhya1s; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), <lb/>relating to the three periods of the day. <i>--Tri- <lb/>sandhya-kusuma1,</i> f. a kind of mallow. <i>--Tri- <lb/>saptata, as, i1, am</i> (fr. the following), the seventy- <lb/>third. <i>--Tri-saptati, is,</i> f. seventy-three; [cf. <i>trayah2- <lb/>saptati.</i>] <i>--Trisaptati-tama, as, i1, am,</i> the seventy- <lb/>third. <i>--Tri-saptan</i> or <i>tri-sapta,</i> three times seven, <lb/>twenty-one [cf. <i>tri-shapta</i>]; <i>trisapta-kr2itvas,</i> <lb/>ind. twenty-one times. <i>--Tri-sama, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>(in geom.) having three equal sides; (<i>am</i>), n. an <lb/>aggregate of equal parts of three substances, viz. <lb/>yellow myrobalan, ginger, and molasses; <i>trisama- <lb/>c4aturas4ra, am,</i> n. a quadrangle having three equal <lb/>sides. <i>--Tri-sara, as, am,</i> m. n. a dish of <lb/>sesamum, rice, &amp;c., <i>= kr2is4ara</i> or <i>kr2isara. --Tri- <lb/>sarga, as,</i> m. the triple product of the three <lb/>qualities of nature. <i>--Tri-savana = tri-shavan2a,</i> q. v. <lb/><i>--Tri-sa1dhana, as, a1, am,</i> triply composed, having <lb/>three component parts. <i>--Tri-sa1man, a1, a1, a,</i> sing- <lb/>ing three Sa1mans or the Sa1man called Trih2-sa1man. <lb/><i>--Tri-sa1ma1,</i> f., N. of a river. <i>--Tri-sa1mya, am,</i> n. <lb/>equilibrium of the three (qualities). <i>--Tri-sa1hasra, <lb/>as, i1, am,</i> Ved. consisting of 3000. <i>--Tri-sita1,</i> f. <i>= tri- <lb/>s4arkara1,</i> three kinds of white sugar, viz. <i>gud2ot- <lb/>panna1, madhu-ja1,</i> and <i>himottha1. --Tri-si1tya, as, <lb/>a1, am,</i> thrice ploughed (as a field &amp;c.). <i>--Tri- <lb/>sugandhi</i> or <i>tri-sugandhika, am,</i> n. <i>= tri-ja1ta,</i> the <lb/>three fragrant substances or spices. <i>--Tri-suparn2a, as,</i> <lb/>m. a N. of certain hymns of the R2ig and Yajur <lb/>Vedas; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), or <i>tri-suparn2aka, as, ika1, <lb/>am,</i> familiar or conversant with the above hymns of <lb/>the Veda; [cf. <i>tri-sauparn2a.</i>] <i>--Tri-suvarc4aka, <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> having a threefold excellent splendor. <lb/><i>--Tri-saugandhya, am,</i> n. <i>= tri-sugandhi. --Tri- <lb/>sauparn2a, as, i1, am,</i> relating to the part of the <lb/>Vedas called Tri-suparn2a; N. of a particular religious <lb/>vow or observance. <i>--Tri-sauvarn2a, am,</i> n. perhaps <lb/>a wrong reading for <i>tri-suparn2a. --Tri-skandhaka,</i> <lb/>N. of a Su1tra work. <i>--Tri-stana, as, a1</i> or <i>i1, am,</i> milked <lb/>from three nipples (Ved.); having three breasts. <i>--Tri- <lb/>stobha-yukta, as, a1, am,</i> having three pauses or <lb/>three rhythms or three divisions (?). <i>--Tri-sthali1,</i> f. <lb/>the three (sacred) places. <i>--Tristhali1-setu,</i> N. of a <lb/>work. <i>--Tri-stha1na, am,</i> n. a sacred spot celebrated <lb/>for a junction of three streams of the Ganges; (<i>as, <lb/>a1, am</i>), reaching through the three worlds. <i>--Tri- <lb/>srotas, a1s, a1s, as,</i>  having three streams; (<i>a1s</i>), f. an <lb/>epithet of the Ganges [cf. <i>tri-patha-ga1, tri-ma1rga- <lb/>ga1, tri-vartma-ga1</i>]; N. of another river. <i>--Tri- <lb/>srotasi1,</i> f., N. of a river. <i>--Tri-halya, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>thrice ploughed (as a field &amp;c.). <i>--Tri-ha1yan2a, as, <lb/>i1, am,</i> three years old; appearing in three ages of <lb/>the world; (<i>i1</i>), f. a three-year-old heifer. <i>--Tri1shu <lb/>(tri-ishº), us, us, u,</i> or <i>tri1shuka, as, a1, am,</i> fur- <lb/>nished with three arrows. <i>--Tri1sht2aka (tri-ishº), <lb/>as, a1, am,</i> Ved. furnished with three Isht2aka1s or sacri- <lb/>ficial bricks. <i>--Try-an6s4a, as, am,</i> m. or n. (?), three <lb/>shares or portions, three-fourths; a third part, the third <lb/>part of a sign of the zodiac (<i>= dr2ikka1n2a,</i> q. v.). <lb/><i>--Tryan6s4a-na1tha, as,</i> m. the regent of a Dr2ikka1n2a. <lb/><i>--Try-aksha, as, i1, am,</i> triocular; (<i>as</i>), m. an <lb/>epithet of Rudra-S4iva; also of a Daitya or Da1nava. [Page0392-b+ 81] <lb/><i>--Tryakshaka, as,</i> m. an epithet of S4iva. <i>--Try- <lb/>akshan, a1, a1, a,</i> triocular; (<i>a1</i>), m. epithet of Rudra. <lb/><i>--Tryaksha-patni1,</i> f. an epithet of Pa1rvati1. <i>--Try- <lb/>akshara, as, a1, am,</i> consisting of three sounds or <lb/>letters or syllables, triliteral; (<i>am</i>), n. a word or <lb/>song consisting of three letters or syllables (e. g. <lb/><i>satyam</i> or <i>sa + ti + am</i>); (<i>as</i>), m. a genealogist; <lb/>the Ghat2aka or matchmaker; [cf. <i>ghat2aka</i> and <lb/><i>khat2aka.</i>] <i>--Try-an4kat2a, am,</i> n. or <i>try-an4gat2a, <lb/>as,</i> m. a sling or three strings like those of a balance <lb/>suspended to either end of a pole for carrying bur- <lb/>dens; a sort of collyrium; (<i>as</i>), m. a N. of S4iva. <lb/><i>--Try-an4ga, a1n2i,</i> n. pl., Ved. three portions of the <lb/>sacrificial victim supposed to belong to the Sv-isht2a- <lb/>kr2it, q. v., viz. the upper part of the right fore-foot, <lb/>a part of the left thigh, and a part of the bowels. <lb/><i>--Try-an4gula, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. three fingers long <lb/>or broad or deep &amp;c. <i>--Tryan4gya, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. <lb/>belonging to the Try-an4gas. <i>--Try-an3jana, am,</i> n. <lb/>the three kinds of collyrium, or Ka1la1n3jana, Push- <lb/>pa1n3jana, and Rasa1n3jana. <i>--Try-an3jala, am,</i> n. and <lb/><i>try-an3jali, i,</i> n. three handfuls. <i>--Try-adhipati, <lb/>is,</i> m. ‘the lord of the three qualities,’ (i. e. <i>sat-tva, <lb/>rajas,</i> and <i>tamas;</i> cf. <i>gun2a</i>), an epithet of Kr2ishn2a <lb/>or Vishn2u. <i>--Try-adhisht2ha1na, as, a1, am,</i> having <lb/>three stations, situated in three places. <i>--Try-adhi1s4a, <lb/>as,</i> m. <i>= try-adhipati,</i> q. v. <i>--Try-adhva-ga1,</i> f. a <lb/>N. of the Ganges, ‘going or flowing through the <lb/>three worlds.’ <i>--Try-ani1ka, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. having <lb/>three faces, followed by three hosts; (Sa1y.) having <lb/>the three properties of heat, rain, and cold. <i>--Try- <lb/>anta, am,</i> n., N. of a Sa1man. <i>--Try-abda, am,</i> n. <lb/>a period of three years; (<i>am</i>), ind. during three <lb/>years; (<i>as, a1, am</i>), three years old. <i>--Try-ambaka, <lb/>as,</i> m. a N. of S4iva (Rudra) as triocular or uttering <lb/>the three (Vedas) or uttering the three mystical <lb/>letters (?), or as having three wives or sisters (as <lb/>if fr. <i>tri-amba1</i>); N. of one of the eleven Rudras; <lb/>the sacrificial ceremony in which the Try-ambaka1s <lb/>or cakes sacred to Rudra Try-ambaka are offered; <lb/>N. of a mountain; (<i>a1</i>), f. an epithet of Pa1rvati1; <lb/>(<i>am</i>), n., N. of a Lin4ga. <i>--Tryambaka-ma1ha1tmya, <lb/>am,</i> n. ‘the glory of Try-ambaka,’ N. of a part of <lb/>the Padma-Pura1n2a. <i>--Tryambaka-sakha, as,</i> m. <lb/>‘the friend of Try-ambaka,’ an epithet of Kuvera, <lb/>the god of wealth. <i>--Try-arun2a, as,</i> m., N. of a <lb/>man with the patronymic Traivr2ishn2a. <i>--Try-arusha, <lb/>as, i1, am,</i> Ved. marked red in three places. <i>--Try- <lb/>avara, as, a1, am,</i> having three who are inferior, <lb/>three at the least; (<i>am</i>), ind. at least three times, <lb/>(see Manu XI. 80.) <i>--Try-avi, is, i1,</i> m. f., Ved. a <lb/>calf eighteen months old. <i>--Tryas4i1ta, as, i1, am</i> <lb/>(fr. <i>try-as4i1ti</i>), the eighty-third. <i>--Try-as4i1ti, is,</i> f. <lb/>eighty-three. <i>--Tryas4i1ti-tama, as, i1, am,</i> the <lb/>eighty-third. <i>--Try-as4ra, as, a1, am,</i> triangular; (<i>as</i>), <lb/>m., N. of a plant, <i>= tridha1ra-snuhi1; (am),</i> n. a <lb/>triangle. <i>--Tryas4ra-kun2d2a, am,</i> n., N. of a mystical <lb/>diagram. <i>--Try-asht2aka, as, a1, am,</i> containing three <lb/>Asht2aka1s; (<i>am</i>), n. a kind of vessel. <i>--Try-asht2an</i> <lb/>or <i>try-asht2a,</i> three times eight, twenty-four; <i>try- <lb/>asht2a-varsha,</i> twenty-four years old. <i>--Try-asra,</i> <lb/>see <i>try-as4ra. --Try-aha, am,</i> n. a period of <lb/>three days; <i>try-aham,</i> ind. during three days; <i>try- <lb/>aha1t</i> or <i>try-ahena,</i> ind. after three days; (<i>as, a1, <lb/>am</i>), lasting three days; (<i>as</i>), m., Ved. a festival lasting <lb/>three days. <i>--Tryaha-spars4a, as,</i> m. or <i>tryaha- <lb/>spr2is4a, am,</i> n. the meeting of part of three lunar <lb/>days in one solar day, (the first lunar day ending just <lb/>after midnight and the third beginning a little before <lb/>the next midnight.) <i>--Tryahi1na, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. last- <lb/>ing three days. <i>--Tryahaihika (ºha-aihº), as, i1, am,</i> <lb/>having provision sufficient for three days, providing <lb/>for three days. <i>--Try-ahna, as, a1, am,</i> happening <lb/>or occurring after three days. <i>--Trya1ksha1yan2a, as,</i> <lb/>m. (fr. <i>try-aksha</i>), a worshipper of S4iva (?). <i>--Trya1- <lb/>ksha1yan2a-bhakta, am,</i> n. a district inhabited by <lb/>worshippers of S4iva. <i>--Try-a1yusha, am,</i> n., Ved. <lb/>threefold vital power or period of life; (according to <lb/>Mahi1-dhara) the threefold period of life, consisting of <lb/>childhood, youth, and old age. <i>--Trya1run2i, is,</i> m. <lb/>(fr. <i>try-arun2a</i>), N. of the Vya1sa in the fifteenth [Page0392-c+ 81] <lb/>Dva1para; N. of a mountain. <i>--Try-a1rsheya, as, i1, <lb/>am,</i> containing three lines or families of R2ishis; <lb/>(<i>a1s</i>), m. pl. an aggregate of three persons, viz. blind, <lb/>deaf, and dumb. <i>--Try-a1likhita, as, a1, am,</i> Ved. <lb/>scratched or marked in three places. <i>--Trya1likhita- <lb/>vat, a1n, ati1, at,</i> consisting of bricks marked in <lb/>three places. <i>--Try-a1vr2it, t, t, t,</i> Ved. carried on in <lb/>three periods, consisting of three series. <i>--Try-a1s4ir, <lb/>i1r,</i> m., Ved. mixed with three products of milk; <lb/>(according to Sa1y.) mixed with Dadhi, Saktu, and <lb/>Payas, (said of the Soma.) <i>--Trya1hika, as, i1, am</i> <lb/>(fr. <i>try-aha</i>), produced or performed &amp;c. in three <lb/>days; tertian; returning after the third day, quartan <lb/>(as a fever); having provisions for three days. <lb/><i>--Try-uttari1-bha1va, as,</i> m. progression by three. <lb/><i>--Try-uda1ya, am,</i> n., Ved. the threefold going to <lb/>the altar, i. e. in the three daily oblations; (Sa1y.) <lb/>having three goings to the altar (as the Soma). <lb/><i>--Try-udhan, a1,</i> m., Ved. three-uddered, (according <lb/>to Sa1y.) said of the year as having three seasons. <lb/><i>--Try-ushan2a</i> or <i>try-u1shan2a, am,</i> n. the three <lb/>spices collectively, i. e. black pepper, long pepper, <lb/>and dry ginger. <i>--Try-r2ic4a, am,</i> n. <i>= tr2ic4a,</i> a <lb/>strophe consisting of three verses. <i>--Try-eta, as,</i> m., <lb/><i>tryen2i1</i> or <i>tryeni1,</i> f., <i>am,</i> n., Ved. variegated or <lb/>spotted in three places.</body><tail><L>21548</L><pc>0388-b</pc></tail></H1>
<H1><h><key1>dina</key1><key2>dina</key2><hom>2</hom></h><body>. <i>dina, as, am,</i> m. n. (probably for <lb/><i>divana</i> and related to 3. <i>div</i> fr. rt. 2. <i>div,</i> said to <lb/>be fr. rt. <i>do</i>), a day; [cf. <i>dur-dº, puru-dº, madh- <lb/>yan-dº, su-dº;</i> cf. also Lith. <i>die†na,</i> f. ‘a day;’ <lb/>Slav. <i>deny,</i> ‘a day;’ Lat. <i>peren-dinus, peren-dina- <lb/>tio, peren = para;</i> perhaps Goth. <i>sin-teins,</i> ‘daily,’ <lb/><i>sin = sam.</i>] <i>--Dina-kara, as, i1, am,</i> making day <lb/>or light; (<i>i1</i>), f., scil. <i>t2i1ka1,</i> N. of a commentary on <lb/>the Bha1sha1-paric4c4heda; (<i>as</i>), m. the sun; N. of <lb/>the author of the work C4andra1rki1. <i>--Dinakara- <lb/>tanaya, as,</i> m. ‘the son of the Sun,’ the planet <lb/>Saturn. <i>--Dinakara-deva, as,</i> m., N. of a poet. <lb/><i>--Dinakara1tmaja1 (ºra-a1tº),</i> f. ‘the daughter of <lb/>the Sun,’ an epithet of the Yamuna1 or Jumna1 river. <lb/><i>--Dina-kartr2i, ta1,</i> m. or <i>dina-kr2it, t,</i> m. ‘the <lb/>day-maker,’ the sun. <i>--Dina-kes4ara</i> or <i>dina-kesara</i> <lb/>or <i>dina-kes4ava, as,</i> m. ‘the hair of the day,’ the <lb/>darkness. <i>--Dina-kshaya, as,</i> m. ‘the decline of <lb/>day,’ the evening, <i>= tithi-kshaya;</i> N. of a chapter <lb/>in the Pura1n2a-sarva-sva. <i>--Dina-jyotis, is,</i> n. ‘day- <lb/>light,’ sunshine. <i>--Dina-duh2khita, as, a1, am,</i> af- <lb/>flicted by day, sorrowing by day; (<i>as</i>), m. the bird <lb/>C4akra-va1ka, the ruddy goose. <i>--Dina-nakta, am,</i> <lb/>n. day and night. <i>--Dina-pati, is,</i> m. ‘the lord of <lb/>the day,’ the sun. <i>--Dina-pran2i1, i1s,</i> m. ‘the bringer <lb/>of day,’ the sun; [cf. <i>tithi-pran2i1.</i>] <i>--Dina-ban- <lb/>dhu, us,</i> m. ‘the friend of the day,’ the sun. <i>--Dina- <lb/>bala, as,</i> m. ‘the strength of the day,’ N. of the <lb/>fifth, sixth, seventh, eighth, eleventh, and twelfth <lb/>signs of the zodiac collectively. <i>--Dina-man2i, is,</i> <lb/>m. ‘the jewel of day,’ the sun. <i>--Dina-mala, am,</i> n. <lb/>‘day-refuse (?),’ a month. <i>--Dina-mu1rdhan, a1,</i> m. <lb/>‘the head of the day,’ the eastern mountain behind <lb/>which the sun is supposed to rise; [cf. <i>udaya.</i>] <lb/><i>--Dina-ratna, am,</i> n. ‘the jewel of the day,’ the <lb/>sun. <i>--Dina-ra1s4i, is,</i> m. ‘the sum or collective <lb/>amount of days,’ i. e. the number of solar days <lb/>which have elapsed from one given point of time to <lb/>another. <i>--Dina-vya1sa-dala, am,</i> n. ‘half-diameter <lb/>or radius of the sky,’ i. e. the radius of a circle made <lb/>by an asterism in its daily revolution. <i>--Dina1n6s4a <lb/>(ºna-an6s4a), as,</i> m. ‘any portion of a day,’ i. e. a <lb/>watch, an hour, morning, forenoon, afternoon, &amp;c. <lb/><i>--Dina1gama (ºna-a1gº), as,</i> m. day-break. <i>--Di- <lb/>na1n2d2a (ºna-an2d2a?), am,</i> n. ‘day-egg,’ i. e. dark- <lb/>ness, (the egg or embryo whence day proceeds.) <lb/><i>--Dina1tyaya (ºna-atº), as,</i> m. ‘the decline of <lb/>day,’ evening. <i>--Dina1di (ºna-a1di), is,</i> m. ‘day- <lb/>break,’ dawn. <i>--Dina1dhi1s4a (ºna-adhº), as,</i> m. <lb/>‘the lord of day,’ the sun. <i>--Dina1nta (ºna-anº), <lb/>as,</i> m. ‘end of day,’ sun-set, evening. <i>--Dina1ntaka <lb/>(ºna-anº), as,</i> m. ‘day-destroyer,’ darkness. <i>--Di- <lb/>na1rambha (ºna-a1rº), as,</i> m. ‘day-break,’ morning. <lb/><i>--Dina1rdha (ºna-arº), as,</i> m. ‘the half of the <lb/>day,’ noon. <i>--Dina1vasa1na (ºna-avº), am,</i> n. ‘close <lb/>of day,’ evening. <i>--Dina1stra (ºna-asº), am,</i> n. <lb/>‘day-missile,’ N. of a magical formula. <i>--Dini1-kr2i,</i> <lb/>cl. 8. P. A. <i>-karoti, -kurute, -kartum,</i> to reduce <lb/>to days. <i>--Dines4a (ºna-i1s4a), as,</i> m. ‘the lord of <lb/>day,’ the sun; the regent of a day. <i>--Dines4a1tmaja <lb/>(ºs4a-a1tº), as,</i> m. ‘the son of the Sun,’ the planet <lb/>Mercury. <i>--Dines4vara (ºna-i1s4º), as,</i> m. ‘the lord <lb/>of the day,’ the sun. <i>--Dinaika (ºna-eka), as,</i> m. <lb/>one day. [Page0413-a+ 73]</body><tail><L>22360</L><pc>0412-c</pc></tail></H1>
<H1><h><key1>lalita</key1><key2>lalita</key2></h><body>Lalita, as, a1, am,  sported, played, playing, sport- <lb/>ing, dallying, wanton, frolicsome, amorous, volup- <lb/>tuous; lovely, handsome, beautiful, graceful, elegant, <lb/>naive, simple, artless, gay, cheerful; soft, gentle; <lb/>pleasing, charming, pleasant, agreeable, wished for, <lb/>desired, loved; trembling, tremulous, shaken; <i>= c4a- <lb/>lita; (am),</i> ind. sweetly, agreeably, gracefully; <lb/>(<i>as</i>), m. epithet of a particular position of the hands <lb/>in dancing; N. of a particular musical scale or Ra1ga, <lb/>(according to some <i>lalita1,</i> f.); (<i>a1</i>), f. a wanton <lb/>woman, a woman in general; musk; N. of a god- <lb/>dess; of a form of Durga1 or Pa1rvati1; of a Gopi1 <lb/>(identified with Durga1 and Ra1dhika1); of a river; <lb/>of various metres, 30 + 32 instants; four times <lb/>˘˘˘˘˘˘¯¯¯¯˘¯; four times ¯¯˘¯˘˘˘¯ <lb/>˘¯˘¯; four times ¯˘˘¯˘¯˘˘˘¯˘¯˘˘˘¯; <lb/>four times ¯˘˘¯˘˘¯˘˘¯˘˘¯˘˘¯˘˘¯˘˘¯; <lb/>twice ¯˘¯˘˘¯˘¯, ˘˘¯˘˘˘˘¯˘¯; (<i>am</i>), n. <lb/>sport, dalliance, amorous gesture, love; grace, beauty, <lb/>charm, charmingness, gracefulness of gait, softness <lb/>and delicacy of motion, languid gestures in a woman <lb/>(expressive of amorous sentiment, ‘lolling,’ ‘lan- <lb/>guishing, ‘&amp;c.); any natural and artless act (as that <lb/>of a child); simplicity, innocency, ingenuousness; N. <lb/>of two metres, four times ˘˘˘˘˘˘˘˘¯˘˘¯; <lb/>four times ˘˘˘˘˘˘¯¯¯¯˘¯; N. of a town. <lb/><i>--Lalita-c4aitya, as,</i> m., N. of a particular C4aitya. <lb/><i>--Lalita-ta1la, as,</i> m., N. of a particular time (in <lb/>music). <i>--Lalita-pada, as, a1, am,</i> consisting of <lb/>amorous words; elegantly composed; a kind of <lb/>metre, four times ˘˘˘˘¯˘˘¯˘˘¯¯. <i>--Lalita- <lb/>pada-bandhana, am,</i> n. an amorous composition <lb/>in verse, a metrical composition treating of love. <lb/><i>--Lalita-pura, am,</i> n., N. of a town. <i>--Lalita- <lb/>pura1n2a, am,</i> n. <i>= lalita-vistara-pura1n2a. --La- <lb/>lita-praha1ra, as,</i> m. a soft or gentle blow. <i>--La- <lb/>lita-ma1dhava, am,</i> n., N. of a drama by Ru1pa. <lb/><i>--Lalita-lalita, as, a1, am,</i> excessively beautiful, <lb/>very handsome. <i>--Lalita-loc4ana, as, a1, am,</i> beauti- <lb/>ful-eyed; (<i>a1</i>), f., N. of the daughter of a Vidya1-dhara <lb/>Va1ma-datta. <i>--Lalita-vanita1,</i> f. a lovely woman. <lb/><i>--Lalita-vistara, as,</i> m. or <i>lalita-vistara-pura1- <lb/>n2a, am,</i> n., N. of a Su1tra work giving a detailed <lb/>record of the simple and natural acts in the life of <lb/>Buddha or S4a1kya-muni. <i>--Lalita-vyu1ha, as,</i> m. <lb/>epithet of a particular kind of Sama1dhi or meditation <lb/>(with Buddhists); N. of a Deva-putra; of a Bodhi- <lb/>sattva. <i>--Lalita1-tr2iti1ya1, am,</i> n., N. of a Tantra <lb/>work. <i>--Lalita1-tr2iti1ya,</i> f. epithet of a particular <lb/>third day. <i>--Lalita1ditya (ºta-a1dº), as,</i> m., N. of <lb/>a king of Kas4mi1ra. <i>--Lalita1ditya-pura, am,</i> n., <lb/>N. of a town founded by Lalita1ditya. <i>--Lalita1-pan3- <lb/>c4ami1,</i> f. the fifth day of the moon's increase in <lb/>the month A1s4vina on which the worship of the <lb/>goddess Lalita1 or Pa1rvati1 is celebrated. <i>--Lalita1pi1d2a <lb/>(ºta-a1pº), as,</i> m., N. of a king of Kas4mi1ra. <i>--La- <lb/>lita1bhinaya (ºta-abhº), as,</i> m. erotic performance, <lb/>representation of love scenes. <i>--Lalita1-ma1dhava = <lb/>lalita-ma1dhava. --Lalita1c4ana-c4andrika1 (ºta1- <lb/>arº),</i> f., N. of a work on the worship of Lalita1. <lb/><i>--Lalita1rtha (ºta-arº), as, a1, am,</i> having an <lb/>amorous meaning. <i>--Lalita1rtha-bandha, as, a1, am,</i> <lb/>composed in words of love or in words having an <lb/>amorous meaning. <i>--Lalita1-vrata, am,</i> n., N. of a <lb/>particular religious observance. <i>--Lalita1-shasht2hi1,</i> <lb/>f. epithet of a particular sixth day. <i>--Lalita1-sap- <lb/>tami1,</i> f. epithet of the seventh day in the light half <lb/>of the month Bha1dra.</body><tail><L>40211</L><pc>0863-a</pc></tail></H1>
<H1><h><key1>smf</key1><key2>smf</key2><hom>2</hom></h><body>. <i>smr2i,</i> cl. 1. P. (ep. also A.) <i>smarati <lb/>(-te), sasma1ra</i> (2nd sing. <i>sasmartha,</i> 1st <lb/>du. <i>sasmariva,</i> 3rd pl. <i>sasmarus</i>), <i>smarishyati, <lb/>asma1rshi1t, smartum,</i> to remember (with acc. or <lb/>gen., and when joined with 2nd Fut. of another rt. <lb/>giving it a past signification, e. g. <i>amum2 smarati ha- <lb/>nishyati,</i> he remembers having killed him, Pa1n2. III. <lb/>2, 112); to recollect, call to mind, bear in mind, <lb/>think of, think upon, be mindful of; to recite men- <lb/>tally or call upon the name (of a deity &amp;c.); to re- <lb/>cord (in the Smr2iti), declare (as Smr2iti or law; <lb/><i>smaranti,</i> they declare in the Smr2iti); to desire, long <lb/>for (with gen.): Pass. <i>smaryate,</i> Aor. <i>asma1ri,</i> Prec. <lb/><i>smr2ishi1sht2a</i> and <i>smarishi1sht2a,</i> to be remembered; <lb/>to be recorded; to be mentioned; to be declared (as <lb/>a law); to be mentioned in the Smr2iti: Caus. <i>sma1ra- <lb/>yati</i> (or <i>smarayati</i>), <i>-te, -yitum,</i> Aor. <i>asasmarat, <lb/>ta,</i> to cause to remember, call to mind, remind; to <lb/>give information; to cause to regret, cause to desire <lb/>or long for (in the latter sense only <i>smarayati</i>): <lb/>Desid. <i>susmu1rshate,</i> to wish to recollect: Intens. <lb/><i>sa1smaryate, sa1smarti;</i> [cf. Gr. <g></g> <lb/><g></g> <lb/><g></g> <lb/>(perhaps also) <g></g> &amp;c.: <lb/>Lat. <i>me-mor, memor-ia, memor-a1-re, mor-a, mos, <lb/>mor-is:</i> Goth. <i>me10r-j-an,</i> ‘to proclaim;’ <i>meritha, <lb/>maurnan:</i> Old Germ. <i>smer-zo,</i> m., <i>smer-za,</i> f. <lb/>‘pain;’ <i>smerzan, ma10riu,</i> ‘to announce;’ <i>ma1ri,</i> <lb/>‘memorable:’ Mod. Germ. <i>Ma7hrchen:</i> Angl. Sax. <lb/><i>mœlan, mal, ge-mœred, mœrdh, mœrsian, mel- <lb/>dian, ameldian, murnan, smeortan,</i> ‘to smart:’ <lb/>Lith. <i>uz-mirs-tu,</i> ‘to forget:’ Hib. <i>smuairean,</i> <lb/>‘dejection;’ (perhaps) <i>smalanach,</i> ‘sorrowful;’ <lb/><i>muirn,</i> ‘natural affection.’]</body><tail><L>53498</L><pc>1153-c</pc></tail></H1>
</mw72>
